<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Dylan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Perils of Overly Local Optimization</title>
      <link>/post/local-optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/local-optimization/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;a-clockwork-egg&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A Clockwork Egg&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- (or &#34;our optimized lives&#34;) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find great comfort in routine. Years of repetition have refined my morning scrambled eggs into a precise and rehearsed ritual. If I turn on the burner before I walk to the fridge, the butter will be just starting to bubble when I finish beating the eggs, and I can clean the mixing bowl in the brief pause before they’re ready to be stirred. I never set out to find the right timing, but if you do the same task a thousand times, you learn from the trial and error of random variation which tiny choices make it go just a little smoother. Anyone with a morning commute can relate to the same familiar, iterative optimization. That is, until some external shock &lt;em&gt;forces&lt;/em&gt; them to change.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;disruption-and-the-london-subway-strike&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Disruption, and the London Subway Strike&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/tube-strikes-february-2014-how-they-will-affect-your-journey-and-stress-levels-9099641.html&#34;&gt;February 4th, 2014&lt;/a&gt;, the workers of the London Tube (the underground subway) went on strike, forcing a number of station closures throughout the city. For three days, some (but not all) commuters were unable to take their usual route to work, and were forced to find alternatives. After the strike, the stations reopened, and life went back to normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three economists saw the opportunity for a natural experiment: only certain commuters were disrupted by the closure, and using the subway’s tracking data, their movements could be compared to the unaffected group. And surprisingly, life &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; quite go back to normal after the ending of the strike. Instead, some of the disrupted group stuck with their newly discovered routes, and their time spent commuting decreased as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The station closures forced commuters to break from their finely tuned routines, but a surprising number found themselves dragged unwillingly along a route that turned out to be &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; than the one they had been taking for years. The researchers even claim that the time savings from these discoveries were so significant that the strike caused a net &lt;em&gt;decrease&lt;/em&gt; in time spent commuting, despite the initial disruptions.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even if only a small fraction found new routes, the benefits from their new routine would acrrue over years to come, while discovering it only required a disruption for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This neat case study provides an opportunity to frame the mathematical challenge of optimization in real world terms, and it gives particular insight into the counterintuitive fact that many optimization algorithms involve &lt;em&gt;random noise&lt;/em&gt;. I’ll begin by describing mathematical optimization in intuitive terms, and then I’ll examine how the London Tube Strike provides a real world analogy for this theoretical challenge.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- This story provides a neat way to frame the mathematical challenge of optimization, and in particular, why so many optimization algorithms involve *random noise*, a choice which might initially seem bizarre. I&#39;ll begin by describing mathematical optimization in intuitive terms, and then show how the results of the London Tube Strike provides an analogy to very real mathematical properties. --&gt;
&lt;!-- ^[I have no personal insight into the rigor of the experiment itself, it&#39;s being used just as a framing device here.] --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-framework-of-optimization&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Framework of “Optimization”&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Math always starts with a definition—so, what is “mathematical optimization”? The &lt;a href=&#34;https://deepai.org/machine-learning-glossary-and-terms/mathematical-optimization&#34;&gt;DeepAI website&lt;/a&gt; writes the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematical optimization is the process of maximizing or minimizing an objective function by finding the best available values across a set of inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easiest to explain these terms by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For London commuters, their “objective function” might be the duration of the commute,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the “available values across a set of inputs” might be the route they take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we want to find the highest peak in a mountain range (an example we’ll discuss in detail in the next section), the input would the latitude and longitude of a point on the map, and the objective function would be the elevation at that point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When baking chocolate chip cookies, the possible inputs might be the amount of each ingredient and the order in which they are combined, and the objective function might be the tastiness of the resulting cookie. This isn’t quite a joke, and Google once ran a &lt;a href=&#34;https://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//pubs/archive/46507.pdf&#34;&gt;cookie optimization experiment&lt;/a&gt; along these lines.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimization is a central challenge in applied mathematics and statistics, but finding solutions can be hard. The vast increase in computational power has broadened our horizons for what optimization challenges are feasible, but many important problems remain out of our reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the challenge of optimization, we generally assume that we are able to check the value of the objective function at some chosen input (often called “queries” to the objective function, or perhaps, the “oracle”). For example…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can take a certain route on the subway and use our stopwatch record the duration of the trip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can bake a batch of cookies following a certain recipe, and taste them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We buy ElevationBot 1.0, a rather simple computer which takes in a pair of latitude and longitude coordinates, and spits out the altitude of that point. (This example is most cleanly understood using such a computer, but to guide our intuition we’ll often imagine ourselves walking around the slopes with an altimeter in hand.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our naive optimization strategy might be to just try a bunch of inputs, and hope that we find a good output. For instance, we define a grid of latitude and longitude coordinates, feed these coordinates into ElevationBot 1.0, and use the highest point we find as our answer. But this naive approach only works when the range of potential inputs is sufficiently narrow. In particular, we need to consider the “dimension” of the input space. The number of points within an exhaustive “grid” of inputs grows exponentially with the dimension of the input. Latitude and longitude represent a mere 2 dimensions, so the number of points in our grid is just the square of the number of points on a side. However, the famous &lt;a href=&#34;https://cooking.nytimes.com/recipes/1015819-chocolate-chip-cookies&#34;&gt;Jacques Torres cookie recipe&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(12\)&lt;/span&gt; ingredients. If we wanted to try all combinations at a mere five different amounts of each ingredient, that would be over two hundred thousand possibilities, which is a bit much for even the hungriest baker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our own lives, we constantly confront similar optimization challenges, but we rarely take this naive approach. Instead, we typically to look around us for small &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; optimizations, whose benefits we can easily identify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- * Finding the best route on the subway is something we optimize. While often algorithmic services can do the work for us, in other cases (or the past), we have to figure it out ourselves, and we somehow pick our starting point. --&gt;
&lt;!-- * For an example, let&#39;s imagine we want to find the highest point in a mountain range. We can check an individual point, and see how high it is. How do we find the highest point? The analogy would be something like, instead of latitude and longitude in a mountain range, in our morning routine it would be that &#34;series of choices for how we get to work&#34;.  --&gt;
&lt;!-- * Now, imagine instead of querying a computer for the height, you yourself were actually in that mountain range. What would you do? Well, you&#39;d look for the peak, but what if you were in a forest? You&#39;d go up. Specifically, you would look at the area around you for *local* guidance. --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;locality-in-optimization&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Locality in Optimization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine biting into a warm cookie, fresh out of the oven. The rich buttery center has just the right chew, while the edges are lightly crisp. You taste the faintest hints of toffee, butterscotch, and vanilla, and the sprinkle of sea salt on top adds an extra kick. It’s almost perfect, but there’s not &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; enough chocolate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;choc_chip_cookies.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wouldn’t just throw up our hands and start from scratch… we’d just add more chocolate! The average baker can’t look at a cookie recipe, and imagine exactly what the result will taste like from afar. But we can &lt;em&gt;taste&lt;/em&gt; a recipe, and imagine what a small specific tweak would do to the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Locality” in optimization refers to “closeness” in the input space. In latitude and longitude, this would be the “as the crow flies” distance, while in the input space of “cookie ingredients” and “subway commuting choices”, the definition is a bit less rigorous, but we can still imagine what constitutes a “small” change. In general, we can estimate the impacts of a &lt;em&gt;limited single change&lt;/em&gt; to the input, but not multiple big adjustments If we increase the amount of chocolate, we know they’ll taste a bit like before, but more chocolate-y. If we increase the amounts of chocolate, butter, baking soda, cut some flour, and tweak the balance between brown and cane sugar, can the average home cook really guess what the result will taste like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the London Tube experiment, the researchers lay some of the blame on the “stylized nature” of the Tube map displayed to commuters. Its spatial distortions make it difficult to spot major inefficiencies in their route, without some external push. By comparison, we can usually estimate the impact of these “local” changes by ourselves. If we get off one stop earlier, maybe our walk to work increases by a minute, but we avoid the wait at a crowded station. These slight changes are a bit like tweaking just a single ingredient in a cookie, and we might be able to tell whether or not they are worth trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;london_tube_map.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Personally, this describes my relationship with my own food. TO ADD MORE... --&gt;
&lt;!-- * In my own life, I find this with food all the time. I have a set rotation of dishes I love, that fit my criteria (hassle-free ingredients, saves well for leftoers, etc). I&#39;m happy to make small chaanes to what I eat. I recently realized how well a lone, unadorned sweet potato went with some of my staples. That&#39;s a one step addition, and I can evaluate its impact as I walk the aisles of the store. Sure enough, it quickly became a staple. --&gt;
&lt;!-- * However, I&#39;m sure there are many full dishes out there that would be just as good as my current rotation. But to find a new dish is a risk. There&#39;s no way for me to see all the the links in the chain. Will the ingredients be easy to find? Will I find the cooking burdensome? What will the end result taste like? Are my cooking supplies well suited to the task? --&gt;
&lt;!-- * We provide some new rules of the game. We know not only the value at these points, we know the shape/slope/etc of the area around it. This is a reasonable relaxation, because we can estimate this shape by querying our computer for the values of the areas near our point (are we going up or down). The rule is that we can&#39;t look far away to see where the peak is (perhaps we&#39;re stuck in the Appalachian forests, and not the sheer granite of the Sierra Nevada).  --&gt;
&lt;!-- * This isn&#39;t arbitrary, it&#39;s a natural understanding of how we actually operate. We are inherently *local* optimizers. We can easily assess the impact of small changes, not not large ones. --&gt;
&lt;!-- * On a morning commute, we can estimate whether taking a turn a few blocks early to avoid a stoplight saves us time. It&#39;s much harder to figure out in advance whether taking the bus or train is easy. --&gt;
&lt;!-- * Now, I&#39;d wager that generally, we&#39;re rather good at making small (later, we will call these &#34;local&#34;, due to their geometric interpretation) adjustments. If I realize that by taking a right a few blocks early, I can avoid the long traffic light, I&#39;ll often do it.  --&gt;
&lt;!-- * However, there&#39;s a reason these are small changes. We can estimate their impact from where we are. If we considered an entirely new route to work, taking a whole different train line, we would have no way to know what that&#39;s like. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before, we imagined a challenge where we tried to find a peak of a mountain range, using ElevationBot 1.0, which could tell us the elevation of any point defined by its latitude and longitude. Now, let’s imagine that there was an upgrade to ElevationBot 2.0, which &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; tells us the slope of the incline of this point (that is, “which direction slopes downward, and how steep is it”, often referred to as the gradient). This better reflects our intuition for local optimization in other settings, but it’s also not a terribly difficult task for the ElevationBot, as it could always query the elevation at nearby points as estimate the slope for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine that we were hiking with an altimeter, and we can look around and see the direction of the hillside slope around us. But, our information is strictly “local”—we’re stuck in the foggy forests of the Appalachians, not the wide open granite of the Sierra Nevada, so we can’t look miles away to spy what peak might be highest. How might we find the highest peak? Well, our intuition is simple: from wherever we are, “go up”. This “algorithm” is called “gradient ascent”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;gradient-ascent&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Gradient Ascent&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradient ascent is a canonical optimization algorithm, and the step by step process can be described as follows (its simplest summary is simply “go up, as fast as you can”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We begin at some initial point. We find the direction of steepest ascent from that point, i.e. “if you took a few steps in any direction, which would make you gain the most elevation?” (the magnitude and direction of steepest ascent form the “gradient”, and the direction is the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; of where a marble would roll). Then, we walk for some distance in that direction (this amount is referred to as the “step size”, meaning a step of the algorithm, not a step with your feet). Once we finish walking, we look around our new location, and we repeat this process again (i.e. determine the direction of steepest ascent, and walk in that direction). Once we reach a point that is essentially flat, there is no direction we can follow which takes us any higher, and we are done (this is called “convergence”). To see this written in basic mathematical notation, see &lt;a href=&#34;#appendix-gradient-ascent-algorithm&#34;&gt;Appendix: Gradient Ascent Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t some arbitrary example, it’s a natural definition of what it means to improve our situation through &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; changes. Wherever we are, we think “what small change could we take to make to make this better?” If our cookies are too salty, we add a bit less salt, but we don’t start over from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualizing-gradient-ascent&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Visualizing Gradient Ascent&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we follow the direction of steepest ascent, but what does that look like in practice? We can visualize our challenge of finding the highest point in a very simple mountain range. In fact, simplest of all, imagine a single hill. This one is perfectly round, but we pretend we don’t know that, and we can only see the local area around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is a contour plot, like what you find on a topographical map. At the center is the highest point, and it slopes down as you get further away. Our current position is the red dot, in the southeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be more clear if we consider viewing the map at an angle (thanks to the &lt;code&gt;rayshader&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tylermw.com/3d-ggplots-with-rayshader/&#34;&gt;package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;uni_vis_3d.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s imagine gradient ascent in action. We look around, and see that the direction of steepest ascent is to the northwest, shown by the red arrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We move that distance up the slope, and look around once again. We see that the direction of steepest ascent is still northwest, so we move once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, shown in 3D (which is admittedly hard to draw…).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;uni_vis_3d_step2.png&#34; /&gt;
We repeat this process until we look around for that direction of steepest ascent, and see that we’re at a point which is basically flat. You can watch the whole process in the gif below. We start in the top right, and climb and climb until we reach the top of the mountain, where we stop.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2d_uni_grad_ascent_anim.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;not-all-mountains-are-friendly&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Not All Mountains Are Friendly&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this simple example, our local minimization strategy (“just go up!”) finds the highest peak without any trouble. However, imagine there were three different peaks, of differing heights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit harder to picture, but a 3D visualization might help picture its shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;mix_vis_3d.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This poses an obvious problem for our algorithm. We hike up until we reach the top of a peak, look around, see that we can’t go up any further, and stop. But this could be true of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the three peaks, and only the peak in the southeast is actually highest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we start near the center of this region, and follow our algorithm. We climb up south and to the east, and reach that highest peak, just like as we did in the case of a single hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2d_mix_grad_ascent_optima_anim.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what if our starting position was just a bit further north? Well, in the gif below, we see that we’d head off in the opposite direction, and end up at the northmost peak. We’d halt at the top, unable to climb any further, and be forever stuck at a lower point than the peak in the southeast. And by the rules of our game, we can only see the area around us, and we’ll never know that there’s a higher peak elsewhere! And most crucially, we couldn’t possibly tell the difference between the two starting points, without prior knowledge of the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2d_mix_grad_ascent_anim.gif&#34; /&gt;
This illustrates a fundamental divide in mathematical optimization. Some surfaces are “convex”, which ensures that gradient ascent will march us directly to the highest point (the “global maxima”), no matter where we begin.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; However, “nonconvex” surfaces lack such guarantees, and might prove computationally intractabe (any “mountain range”, by definition, falls into this category, as it has multiple peaks). Informal definitions of these terms can be found in the appendix (&lt;a href=&#34;#appendix-the-perils-of-nonconvexity&#34;&gt;Appendix: The Perils of “Nonconvexity”&lt;/a&gt;), but the most intuitive takeaway is the issue of “spurious optima”. To clarify the jargon…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optima: either maxima or minima (these challenges are equivalent).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global optimum (or maximum/minimum): the optimum among the &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; input space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local optima (or maxima/minima): these points are optima in a small neighborhood around themselves, but not if you consider points far away. There is no local direction which takes you higher (or lower, if minimizing), but none are the global optimum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the context of optimization, local optima are also called &lt;em&gt;spurious&lt;/em&gt; optima, because they have the same local properties as the global optimum, but they are not the solution to the optimization challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the convex realm, local information provides us with global guidance, and we can follow the path of steepest ascent all the way to the maxima. In the nonconvex setting, we might instead find ourselves trapped in a spurious optima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- * Which optimization challenges are hard? Math draws a fairly simple distinction. ^[Like maximization and minimization, convex and concave will be used interchangeably. The multiplying a convex function by minus $1$ makes it concave. Concave functions are easy to maximize, but we can switch between the two interchangeably.] --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;finding-the-top&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Finding the Top&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are wary of getting stuck at a spurious optima, how can we modify our approach to ensure we find the highest peak?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we saw above, that certain starting positions were successful, and others lead us astray. What if we simply used our gradient ascent algorithm multiple times, starting from randomly chosen starting points? Then we could check the results of each of our attempts, and pick the highest point we find. The gif below shows what that might look like.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If we try a number of randomly chosen points, we are highly likely to find one that leads to the highest peak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2d_mix_grad_restarts_anim.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense, the challenge becomes one of &lt;em&gt;initialization&lt;/em&gt;. This is common in the optimization literature. Even if the optimization surface is nonconvex, we just need to find a starting point that’s reasonably close to the optima (within its “basin of attraction”), and our naive gradient ascent algorithm can do the rest. Countless papers have been written on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also a natural fit for our intuition—if you set out to find the perfect chocolate chip cookie, I bet you’d do something similar. You’d try a bunch of different recipes that each look promising, and then try and find small improvements based on the results (a bit less salt or a bit more chocolate). It’s the equivalent of trying different starting points, and then following gradient ascent (albeit, random initialization would be a poor choice when we have such rich domain knowledge to lean on).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the challenge boils down to how hard it is to find the right starting point. Are any of the popular cookie recipes out there reasonably close to your own personal, optimal cookie? Hard to say. A large region of the mountain range above lead to the best peak, but what if there were dozens of mountains and the tallest one was steep with a narrow base? The challenge of optimization depends on the setting in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;embracing-random-noise&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Embracing Random Noise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!-- [maybe not rigidly speak in terms of gradient ascent?] --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, we could view the challenge from a different perspective. Instead of trying to optimize different starting points using their local information, what if we were a bit more flexible in our climbing path, and were willing to experiment along the way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there’s a reason that gradient ascent is so rigid in its path—it always goes in the direction that gives you the largest gain in the shortest amount of time. Any other direction appears inferior. If the cookies aren’t chocolate-y enough, you’d feel a little silly trying any other fix besides adding more chocolate chips to the dough. But as we’ve seen, local improvements will only take you so far. My ideal chocolate chip cookie is thick and chewey, but imagine that I had only ever tried recipes which were thin and crispy. I could try and improve them by tinkering with the balance of butter and sugar, or adding more chocolate, which might make them taste a bit better. But it would require the simultaneous change of many ingredients to make the huge leap from one type of cookie to the other.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we were a little more open to experimentation, even if we can’t easily see how it would help? Let’s recall the example of the London subway. These commuters had settled into their preferred morning routes, and surely if they could spot any tiny tweak which would save them time, they would have already tried it. The three day strike represented an external shock to the system, which pushed them out of their local equilibrium. It wasn’t designed to improve their commute (if anything, it was the opposite). And yet, by random chance, there was a group of commuters who found themselves pushed into a surprisingly superior path, which they stuck with. Likely, that route didn’t seem faster than afar, and they would be loathe to waste their time on any route that looks inferior. Only through this forced random experimentation did they escape their local optima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What might this look like mathematically? Well, we could introduce random “noise” into our movement. Let’s imagine gradient ascent once more. From our starting point, we walk in the direction of greatest ascent, and then, &lt;em&gt;we walk a bit furher in a random direction&lt;/em&gt;. This won’t feel very rewarding in the moment… we want to go “up”, we can see which direction takes us “up”, and yet, we go in a random direction? But maybe this extra experimentation will give us a chance to escape our deterministic march towards a spurious optima, and we will eventually find the highest peak. We will still &lt;em&gt;tend&lt;/em&gt; to go “up”, but we might not follow such a direct path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be mathematically precise (again, you can just skip the mathematical part if you’d like), we simply add the random noise to our gradient ascent step from before. That is, now we set &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(x^{(k+1)} \leftarrow x^{(k)} + \eta \nabla f(x^{(k)}) + \sigma^2 \epsilon_k\)&lt;/span&gt;, where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\epsilon_k \sim N(0, 1)\)&lt;/span&gt;. That is, we add a normally distributed random noise term to each gradient ascent step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To visualize this, we turn to the one dimensional case. A one-dimensional mountain range might not be quite as intuitive, but it’s a lot easier to see on your screen, and the same rules apply. Below, we consider a mountain range where the middle peak is the highest. Following gradient ascent, if we start on the far right, we quickly find the nearby peak, but are stuck there, unable to find the highest point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;test_grad_ascent_anim.gif&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we start from the same place, but add a bit of noise with every step, our path isn’t quite so direct. We take a bit longer to reach the top of the low peak, but from there, the random noise gives us a chance to “escape”. That is, with each move, we feel a pull back towards the low peak (as that is the direction of ascent). But if we get lucky, and find a sequence of random noise terms that “push” us far enough to the the left, we escape this valley and feel the pull of the highest peak. The addition of random noise allows us to escape eternal mediocrity, stuck at the top of the low peak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;test_noisy_ascent_anim.gif&#34; /&gt;
Of course, this gif takes a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time to run—it requires a very lucky sequence of steps for us to escape the local optima! Thus, this is far from an easy fix. In fact, this highlights the importance of precisely tuning this approach. Blindly adding random noise will &lt;em&gt;eventually&lt;/em&gt; let you find the summit, but along the way you’ll be stuck with long stretches of experimentation before you get anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;estimation-error-as-noise&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Estimation Error as Noise&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply adding random noise to gradient ascent isn’t a “real” algorithm that would be ever used in practice, but it helps illustrate the powerful premise of “stochastic optimization” (i.e. optimization techniques which leverage random chance). Many varieties of stochastic optimization see widespread use,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but here, I’ll focus on one particularly relevant example, Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of Stochastic Gradient Descent is a natural extension of the gradient ascent algorithm we studied above. First, we note again “gradient &lt;em&gt;ascent&lt;/em&gt;” and “gradient &lt;em&gt;descent&lt;/em&gt;” are equivalent—you simply take the negative of the gradient to switch between maximization and minimization. Rather, it’s the “stochastic” that’s new.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In gradient ascent, we needed to compute the slope of the local area (i.e. the gradient) with each step. Let’s consider again our ElevationBot 2.0 which takes in latitude and longitude coordinates, and tells us the elevation and local slope of that point. However, we’re not the only ones trying to play this addictive “find the highest peak” game, so we have to wait in a long line before each query. However, nearby we see a rusted old ElevationBot 1.5 terminal. It’s an intermediate model, between version 1.0 (which just computes the altitude) and 2.0 (which also computes the direction of ascent), because it can only &lt;em&gt;estimate&lt;/em&gt; the direction of ascent, and it’s occasionally a bit off. However, there’s no one in line to use it, so we can rattle off our queries much faster. Should we skip the line, and use the faster but less reliable estimates of the 1.5 model?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This silly story might make the setting sound overly contrived, but it’s actually a very foundational tradeoff.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It is often much faster to compute an &lt;em&gt;approximate&lt;/em&gt; slope rather than an &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; one.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref13&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This is the premise of Stochastic Gradient Descent—the exact gradient is replaced by a stochastic gradient, which is much faster to compute but is only an approximation of the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is no niche use case. Stochastic Gradient Descent has been the canonical industry standard technique for optimizing artificial neural nets for decades. When you hear about the rise of “deep learning” in the news, Stochastic Gradient Descent is the most reliable and versatile computational tool in the field. The challenge of neural networks is that their optimization space might consist of millions of dimensions (above, we visualized optimizing over a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; dimension!). In fact, Microsoft recently boasted of a neural network with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/blog/zero-deepspeed-new-system-optimizations-enable-training-models-with-over-100-billion-parameters/&#34;&gt;17 billion (!)&lt;/a&gt; dimensions. The inevitable result of these optimization structures is that there are an enormous number of spurious local optima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which begs the question—if neural networks are loaded with spurious local optima, and following the gradient will often lead to those spurious points, why does SGD work so “unreasonably well”?&lt;a href=&#34;#fn14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref14&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are a variety of answers, depending on who you ask, but the most common reason researchers point to (an explanation dating back &lt;a href=&#34;https://leon.bottou.org/publications/pdf/nimes-1991.pdf&#34;&gt;decades&lt;/a&gt;), is that the inherent noise in the imprecise stochastic approximation allows it to escape spurious local optima.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref15&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This is not noise that we added explicitly, it’s just the approximation error that arises from not computing the exact gradient. And yet, these random shocks turn out to be an advantage, rather than a hindrance. Even at the computational cutting edge of the field, random noise can be a powerfully helpful force, pushing us away from spurious optima and further towards our goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wrapping Up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The informal parallels between mathematical theory and our lived experience are illustrative, but not definitive. I think there is a kernel of a genuine lesson to be found here—we tend towards overly local optimization strategies in our daily lives, and external random shocks can push us to a better solution. And yet, it’s important not to take this too far. In the world of pure mathematical theory, we can carefully study the effects of any potential noise, and calibrate it to fit the situation. In our daily lives, we can’t easily assess the impact of this noise, and it could just as easily provide a pointless disruption (indeed, recall the example of the one-dimensional noisy ascent gif, and the long circuitous route it took to reach the top!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famed computer scientist Alan Perlis once said “Optimization hinders evolution”. In our case, this means finding a balance between the fundamental “explore vs exploit” trade-off. That is, we could spend our energy searching for better strategies (“explore”), or we could focus on deriving the benefit from the currently known optimal strategy (“exploit”). This trade-off is omnipresent in the decisions we make, and it’s very hard to get right. My instincts are that our &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF00055564&#34;&gt;status quo bias&lt;/a&gt; and inherently “local” perspective means we’ll typically err on the side of “too much exploration”, but there’s no universal rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the takeaway is simply one of perspective—rather than resisting every disruption outside of our control, we should welcome it as an opportunity to explore something new. After all, there’s no point getting mad at a road closure on your commute, the world won’t notice.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref16&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrambled eggs are a wonderful way to start the day, and I doubt I could do much more to optimize the way I make them to my own unique tastes. But I’d be foolish to think that there weren’t other breakfast options I might enjoy just as much, even if the first few times I make them they don’t go as smoothly as my current ritual. All it takes is accepting the limits of your local perspective, and taking a leap of faith towards that hidden higher peak.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref17&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sources&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Sources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://timharford.com/books/messy/&#34;&gt;“Messy”&lt;/a&gt;, by Tim Harford. Broadly, this whole post was heavily inspired by Tim Harford’s writings on the London Tube experiment. I first read his description when I was studying Langevin diffusions, and I have wanted to show some visualizations of the premise ever since. I think this post is sufficiently far from his writings to add something new (he uses the example to make a point about how external shocks pushing us out of equilibrium prompt greater creativity, whereas I’m trying to focus simply on the viewpoint on mathematical optimization), but the original idea is certainly his.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://users.ox.ac.uk/~econ0360/FerdinandRauch/Tube.pdf&#34;&gt;“The Benefits of Forced Experimentation: Striking
Evidence from the London Underground Network”&lt;/a&gt;, by Larcom, Rauch, &amp;amp; Willems (2017). Further, a short &lt;a href=&#34;http://cep.lse.ac.uk/pubs/download/cp455.pdf&#34;&gt;write-up&lt;/a&gt; of the London Tube Strike research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en//pubs/archive/46507.pdf&#34;&gt;“Bayesian Optimization for a Better Dessert”&lt;/a&gt;, by Kochanski et al. (2017).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rayshader.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rayshader&lt;/code&gt; package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://leon.bottou.org/publications/pdf/nimes-1991.pdf&#34;&gt;“Stochastic Gradient Learning
in Neural Networks”&lt;/a&gt;, by L&#39;eon Bottou.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;appendix-gradient-ascent-algorithm&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Appendix: Gradient Ascent Algorithm&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gradient ascent algorithm, written informally in mathematical notation.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref18&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Imagine we are at some point &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(x \in \mathbb{R}^d\)&lt;/span&gt; (meaning, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt; is a point in &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(d\)&lt;/span&gt;-dimensional space).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(f: \mathbb{R}^d \to \mathbb{R}\)&lt;/span&gt; be our objective function. Let &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\eta &amp;gt; 0\)&lt;/span&gt; be our step size constant.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref19&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; We begin at some initial point &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(x^{(0)} \in \mathbb{R}^d\)&lt;/span&gt;. For &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(k = 0, \ldots,\)&lt;/span&gt;, until convergence, repeat steps 2 through 4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compute the gradient &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\nabla f(x^{(k)})\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(x^{(k+1)} \leftarrow x^{(k)} + \eta \nabla f(x^{(k)})\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\nabla f(x^{(k)})\)&lt;/span&gt; is sufficiently small, halt the algorithm, and select &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(x^{(k+1)}\)&lt;/span&gt; as our optima. Otherwise, set &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(k \leftarrow k+1\)&lt;/span&gt;, and repeat steps 2-4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;appendix-the-perils-of-nonconvexity&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Appendix: The Perils of “Nonconvexity”&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuitively, we call a region a “convex set” if the line between any two points within that region stays &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; that region. Thus, the rectangular Wyoming is convex, while Cape Cod makes Massachussetts nonconvex. Then, we call a &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt; “convex” if the region that lies above the surface of the function forms a “convex set”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, convex functions are easy to optimize, because *local information provides global guidance&amp;quot;. That is, if we follow the path upward, we know that we’ll eventually reach the true optimal value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one further note to make this correct. The mountain range elevation objective function we study is actually “concave”, which is just a convex function flipped upside down. In this colloquial description of optimization challenges, we use the two terms interchangeably, because they are equally easy to solve.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref20&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[I want this post to be quite glib/silly, but this opening might be a little much, or maybe I just haven’t been able to word it right. Or might be best to just launch into the Londno Subway example.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This seems much harder to rigorously prove, but this is meant simiply as an informal framing device.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rare, and extremely tenuous connection between areas of my research, and reality.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or they could add in other factors, like cost or “pleasantness”.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve tasted the resulting cookies, not bad for a cafeteria batch.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The above images took huge step sizes for visual clarity, this shows a more realistic sequence.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is informal, so we omit regularity conditions that would not add to the explanation (but technically, this guarantee would also require the gradient of the objective to be Lipschitz, and for a suitable adaptive step-size).&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only a few starting points shown, to keep the gif short.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn9&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, the question is “Would a sequence of small, incrementally beneficial changes take you all the way from ‘thin and crispy’ to ‘thick and chewey’?” In mathematics, this is the matter of convexity, but in the real world, it can be very hard to say. My assumption is that this often &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; apply in cooking. If you take the middle point between two excellent dishes, there’s no reason to think that it would be tasty! But it’s hard to say with confidence what the optimization space of chocolate chip cookies looks like. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn10&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Simulated annealing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;parallel tempering&lt;/a&gt; are two particular favorites of mine.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn11&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;What follows is a bit of a simplification of SGD, but I think it’s true to the essence of the algorithm.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn12&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Which might be more clear if just stated explicitly… not at all clear to me that this example is clarifying?]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn13&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the case of SGD, the reason this happens is that it estimates the gradient by only using a &lt;em&gt;subset&lt;/em&gt; of the whole dataset.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn14&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the words of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/samcharrington/status/917816482242990080&#34;&gt;Geoffrey Hinton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn15&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;And “saddle points”, which I am skirting past here, as they are a similar concern for this high level explanation.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn16&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Why should we feel anger at the world? As if the world would notice?” is often cited to Marcus Aurelius, although I can’t personally find the source.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn17&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For full transparency, a few months ago I switched to fried eggs on top of frozen vegetables as my breakfast of choice, so maybe I took this lesson to heart.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn18&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is for an extremely crude version with fixed step size &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\eta\)&lt;/span&gt;, and an imprecise definition of convergence. There is no reason to use fixed step size in practice, but that adjustment isn’t relevant to the demonstration.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn19&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is for an extremely crude version with fixed step size &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\eta\)&lt;/span&gt;. There is no reason to use fixed step size in practice, but that adjustment isn’t relevant to the demonstration.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn20&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can turn a concave function into a convex one by simply multiplying it by &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(-1\)&lt;/span&gt;, and minimizing rather than optimizing.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Gentle Introduction to Parlays and Independence </title>
      <link>/post/parlays-independence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/parlays-independence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Betting parlays of positively correlated events will generally be profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement is far from revolutionary, and will be obvious to those familar with the fundamentals of betting. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve talked to many folks with no prior experience who wanted to learn more. I thought it would be interesting and fun to write up a basic tutorial in this concept which assumes minimal background in probability (and should provide good intuition even with no mathematical foundation). This post is intended as an exercise in explaining concepts at an introductory level, and should be ignored by those who are already comfortable with the tools of probability (although many might find the 2018 election parlay opportunities of interest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;betting&#34;&gt;Betting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are familiar with the concept of a bet. I might flip a coin, and the loser pays the winner a dollar, which feels like a fair deal. Implicit in our evaluation of this bet as &amp;ldquo;fair&amp;rdquo; is the concept of Expected Value (EV). While this will avoid the mathematical definition whenever possible, we tend to have an intuitive sense of EV when we confront it in our daily lives. The fact that the coin flipping game is &amp;ldquo;fair&amp;rdquo; is obvious due to its symmetry. But if I instead offered to roll a die, and said that on a one through four you pay me a dollar, and on a five or six I pay you two dollars, many people would intuitively see this bet as fair as well. I have twice the chance to win, but have to pay out twice as much. Mathematically, we simply find the sum of all the outcomes multiplied by their probability of occurrence. I have \(2/3\) chance to pay you a dollar, and \(1/3\) chance to win two dollars, and \(-1*\frac{2}{3} + 2*\frac{1}{3} = 0\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to betting, it&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that Expected Value is the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; viable way to consider the outcome, and any other metric is bound to be a losing strategy in the long run. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it applies in every practical situation. If I offered you a deal where I would double your life&amp;rsquo;s savings with a 55% chance, and you would lose it all with 45% chance, this is clearly a positive expected value bet, and it is also one that you should demonstrably &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; take. The marginal utility of money states that the value of doubling your life savings does not equate to the loss from losing your life&amp;rsquo;s savings. This is a reminder that betting is particularly problematic in any situation where the stakes are not so low that you can focus solely on EV. If someone offered you the same deal on each of your individual dollars in your life savings independently, then it would be a consistently profitable proposition with essentially no downside, due to the law of large numbers. (And if one&amp;rsquo;s life savings is not suitably large so that the law of large numbers applies, betting should be far from your mind). This is not the purpose of this summary, but for anyone who does plan to place bets, it is essential that they give some preliminary consideration to the marginal utility of money, bankroll management, and the law of large numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;betting-notation&#34;&gt;Betting Notation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In America, bets are usually denoted using the Moneyline system, where odds are reported in the form of \(\pm X-[\)hundred]. A +\(200\) line says that if you bet \$100 and win, you receive back \$200 plus your original bet. A \(-250\) line says that if you bet \$250 and win, you win \$100 (and of course also win back your original bet). This system makes it intuitive to measure your payout on a specific bet, but it is somewhat opaque when newer bettors try and understand the corresponding probabilities associated with each bet. We can work in terms of &amp;ldquo;Implied Odds&amp;rdquo;, which are simply the corresponding percentage chance that you would need to win for the bet to be breakeven in expected value. A +200 Moneyline has corresponding Implied Odds of 33.3%. Abroad, odds are frequently reported in fractional terms, a +200 Moneyline corresponds to 2/1 (&amp;ldquo;two to one&amp;rdquo;) odds. We note that Moneyline odds will be in the form of plus or minus at least \(100\). American sports will also report bettling lines such as the New England Patriots being \(-7.5\) for their game. This is a &lt;em&gt;point spread&lt;/em&gt;, where there is even money to be made betting whether the Patriots will score at least \(7.5\) more points than their opponent. I personally find it nearly impossible to quickly understand Moneyline odds in terms of probabilities, so I built a light 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/odds-converter/klechkhopfnjihobbcfeheooaigjjgdg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; that can quickly perform these conversions on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;parlays&#34;&gt;Parlays&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standard bets offer a payout based on a binary result. You might bet that the Golden State Warriors win the NBA title (&amp;ldquo;NBA Futures&amp;rdquo;), or that the Eagles score at least six more points than the Raiders in their upcoming game (&amp;ldquo;beating the spread&amp;rdquo;). A bettor who has fallen on hard times might have little to do for the whole weekend but watch sports, and could place separate bets that Alabama beats Oklahoma and that Clemson beats Notre Dame in the College Football Playoff. However, they could also &amp;ldquo;parlay&amp;rdquo; events, in which they &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; get paid out if &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; those events occur (if Clemson beats ND but Alabama loses, then they would receive nothing). This seems like a scam, but the allure is that under a parlay the payoffs are multiplicative, and much more lucrative than simply the sum of those individual payouts. This is alluring to many bettors because it promises large paydays. In the above example, Alabama and Clemson were both large favorites, at -555 and -440 respectively (i.e. you have to place a bet of \$555 or \$440 to win a prize of \$100 if you are correct). Parlays are appealing to bettors because we have poor intuition for the likelihood of a number of independent (explained below) very likely events &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; occurring. This fallacy is ubiquitous. In college football, when halfway through the season, a dozen contenders are 6-0, analysts and fans tend to look at their upcoming schedule, see that they are favored in each of those six games, and tend to muse about the situation in which each of those individually likely events occurs. In politics, readers are perplexed when analysts predict that of some 100 house races that lean solidly to one side, there will very likely be &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; number of shocking upsets, even if we don&amp;rsquo;t know which one. Our mind works by considering individual events. If I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; remaining football game your team is likely to lose, you may be accustomed to think that the most likely result is that you don&amp;rsquo;t lose a single one, even when that is an unlikely event (as shown by the fact that even the top contenders tend to lose a game by the end of the college football season).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, parlays are appealing to bookies because they encourage more betting, and bookies profit from the volume of bets placed. There is no &lt;em&gt;catch&lt;/em&gt; here, and the bookies give a fair price on a parlay. Instead of the Clemson &amp;amp; Alabama example, we consider one where the probabilities are intuitive, with an extremely boring bookie that allows you to bet on the results of die rolls with no rake (which is the tax they take as profit on any bet placed). In each case, you bet \$1. For Bet A, they toss two dice, and you win \$12 (including your bet) when they sum to at least 11. For Bet B, they toss a single die, and you win \$6 (including your bet) if they roll a six. Both these bets have an expected value of 0. For Bet A, this has a 1 in 12 chance of occuring, so if you have placed a \$1 bet, you have a 1 in 12 chance of winning \$12, which is fair (and the same for Bet B with a 1 in 6 chance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted to up the stakes and instead ask for a parlay on these events, you could significantly increase your possible payout. Bookies are perfectly fair when it comes to parlays. They set their own lines, and choose how much &amp;ldquo;rake&amp;rdquo; to take from the bets, but when it comes to parlays, bookies follow a simple formula which preserves the expected value of the payouts. They simply consider it the same as a single bet on the event where both happen, with that probability computed by multiplying the individual probabilities together. In the case above, a parlay of Bet A and Bet B would yield a whopping \$72 payout when it hits. This calculation is predicated on the idea that the probability that both A and B occur is the product of their individual probabilities, so \(1/6 * 1/12 = 1/72\). If we use the mathematical shorthand \(P(A)\) to denote &amp;ldquo;Probability of Bet A succeeding&amp;rdquo;, and \(P(A,B)\) for &amp;ldquo;probability of both Bet A and Bet B succeeding&amp;rdquo;, we write this as \(P(A)*P(B)=P(A,B)\). Those familiar with probability will note that this formula holds for any two events which are &lt;em&gt;independent&lt;/em&gt;, that is, where information about the result of one event tells us nothing about the result of the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independence is a mathematically defined concept, but we have an intuition for its meaning. If I ask you to guess the probability that a baby is born on a white Christmas (that is, on a December 25th where it snows), you would be foolish to take the probability that the baby is born on December 25th, and multiply it by the probability that it is snowing on any given day. It is significantly more likely that it snows on December 25th than the average day because it is in the middle of winter. The proper calculation would be to find the product of the probabilities that it is December 25th, and that it is snowing on any given December 25th (a conditional probability, whose  definition we sidestep here). Luckily, in the case of our dice rolling bookie, independence is pretty irrefutable. Assuming that the dice are fair and properly weighted, the results of the first pair of rolls have no effect on the outcome of some later rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;parlays-of-dependent-events&#34;&gt;Parlays of Dependent Events&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This prompts the question, how do parlays work when the events are not independent? The short answer is that bookies generally do not offer parlays on dependent events, and that parlaying events that are positively correlated (i.e. the chance of one occurring makes it more likely that the other occurs) is profitable for the bettor. Luckily, most bets offered by the bookie tend to be independent. The scores of football games on a given Sunday seem to have little relation to one another. The most common bets to show dependence in fact show a &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; correlation, when only one can occur. A parlay on NBA futures where both the Golden State Warriors and the Cleveland Cavaliers win the NBA title is clearly nonsensical (the fact that the probability of both occurring is 0 is a form of dependence).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens if a bookie allows betting on positively correlated events? This is best demonstrated by example. We consider Bet A and Bet B again, but with a twist. Bet A remains the same, but now define Bet B to be whether the first die rolled &lt;em&gt;of those used for Bet A&lt;/em&gt; is a six (rather than rolling a new die. Clearly, the individual probabilities are the same. However, these events are no longer independent. Intuitively, the success of Bet B (so the first roll is a 6) greatly increases the chance that Bet A succeeds (although it does not guarantee it). More precisely, the probability that both Bet A and Bet B occur is simply 1/18, as there are two possible rolls that are valid ([6,5] and [6,6]). However, \(1/18 &amp;gt; 1/72 = 1/6*1/12\). Thus, if the bookie provided an \$18 payout on this parlay, it would be break even for the bettor. If they provided the $72 pay out prescribed by the standard parlay formula, a bettor would print money in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correlated events still have a &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; and fair price (in the example above, it was the substantially reduced price of $18). However, this computation required knowledge of their exact correlation. This is straightforward when it comes to the rolling of two dice, but difficult when it comes to the complex real world bets that bookies profit from. We can intuitively guess that the Super Bowl prop bet &amp;ldquo;Tom Brady throws for two or more touchdowns&amp;rdquo; is likely correlated with the bet &amp;ldquo;The Patriots (his team) win the Super Bowl&amp;rdquo;. In the world where we know Brady had a prolific scoring night, his team&amp;rsquo;s chances of winning are much higher (having essentially &amp;ldquo;removed&amp;rdquo; all of the worlds in which the Patriots offense was shut out, many of which were losing scenarios). But it is very difficult to estimate precisely how correlated those events are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bookies prefer the simple solution: they do not offer correlated parlays. You can bet separately on these events, but they offer a singular pricing formula for parlays. Either the events are independent (in which case the probabilities are multicative, and they use their standard pricing formula), or they do not offer the parlay. In the world of sports, the divide between dependence and independence is usually fairly clear. Events in separate games on the same day should be independent. Events &lt;em&gt;within the same game&lt;/em&gt; tend not to be. There are correlations between a wide variety of events within the same game, even if it isn&amp;rsquo;t as obvious as &amp;ldquo;touchdowns scored&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;final result&amp;rdquo;. If a basketball team has twin stars, there will tend to be a slight negative correlation between their points scored, because there are a limited number of possessions and each shot taken by one player is a shot the other does not take. There are of course mitigating factors: a high scoring night for one player might indicate that the opposing defense is poor, or the two stars might both pass less to their supporting cast on nights when those role players are shooting poorly. But neither effect tends to outweigh the simple fact that there are a limited number of shots in the game. Bookies feel no obligation to attempt to set the correct price on these myriad combinations, and instead allow for parlays solely in the case of obviously plausible independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;parlays-in-political-elections&#34;&gt;Parlays in Political Elections&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, the statement &amp;ldquo;bookies do not allow for correlated parlays&amp;rdquo; is a sweeping generalization. Bookies make mistakes, and the &amp;ldquo;rake&amp;rdquo; that they take allows for a reasonable margin of error. It is better practice for them to consistently offer bets that attract bettors, than worry about the singular case in which they make a small mistake and suffer a loss. Bookies limit the amount that can be wagered at any given time, so even when they set an inaccurate line, they are not fleeced by sharp gamblers with deep pockets. It is always worth keeping an eye out for situations where bookies might slip up and offer such a profitable parlay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such example came in the form of the 2018 midterm elections. Bookies offered bets on the results of individual races, general trends (&amp;ldquo;How many seats do Republicans gain in the Senate?&amp;quot;), and more. Some correlations are powerful and obvious. The result that Josh Hawley (Missouri), Dean Heller (Nevada), and Mike Braun (Indiana) win their Senate races is highly correlated with the GOP retaining control of the Senate. If they win those three close races, the odds that they somehow lose enough much more safe Senate seats for the Democrats to flip control is next to 0. I did not see any bookie foolish enough to allow parlays on these events. Generally, bookies are acutely aware that vertical structures like this (where one result is an aggregate of many individual results) have clear positive correlation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there was at least one bookie that allowed for parlays of &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; Senate races. For bookies accustomed to sports, this might seem sensible, as it is superficially similar to parlaying simultaneous game results. However, separate senate races can show obvious and consistent correlation. Some may dislike the language of this claim, as philisophically, it depends on your probabilistic interpretatin of a political race. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to see the connection between the senate choice of individual voters in Arizona and Nevada. However, under that framework, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to see how random chance enters the equation at all (voters are not flipping a coin at the ballot box, by and large). This ties into a deeper issue of how we interpret probabilistic forecasts, but my short answer would be that we use probability describe level of uncertainty about complex phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polling is the base staple of an election prediction. Even in the fantastical world where polls represent a perfectly random sampling of the entire voting population, there is the uncertainty that stems from the inherent randomness of such a random sample (luckily, this form of uncertainty is easy to mathematically model, and disappears as our sample gets very large). Then there is the uncertainty comes from the practical realities of imperfect polling, which crudely violates the simple assumptions taught in an introductory probability class (consider the work 538 does to grade pollsters as part of this uncertainty). And the final nebulous level of uncertainty comes from translating the results of the poll (which studies on a specific date who people say they plan to vote for) to the results of the election itself (determined by the choice of people who actually place a vote). These are two separate questions, and even if a poll precisely answers its own question, the translation of that to answer the second question can be clouded by the uncertainty of news that breaks after the poll is conducted, or voters who think it over some more and get cold feet, or a storm which prevents those without a car from making their way to the polling station, or any number of ways that these questions can differ. Election models have to grapple with these layers of uncertainty, and as a result a site like 538 reports that Ted Cruz has a &amp;ldquo;7 in 9&amp;rdquo; chance to beat Beto O&amp;rsquo;Rourke, and not complete certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The claim that election results are correlated fits neatly into this framework. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to define the connection between the individual decisions of voters in two states about two different pairs of candidates. But it&amp;rsquo;s easy to see how the errors in the probabilitic forecast would be connected. This is particularly true in the heavily partisan landscape of our current political system. The senate races in Nevada and Arizona aren&amp;rsquo;t entirely separate. In each of these demographically similar states, the populace is choosing between a democrat and a republican. Thus, certain forecasting errors made in one state tend to be mirrored in the other. The mistakes that pollsers make which could underestimate latino turnout will cause a similar divergence from the election forecasts and the final result in the two states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This implies that even in a world where the election outcomes are random according to the exact probabilities prescribed by the betting markets, a parlay offers a chance for profit. The positive correlation of these two results simply needs to outweigh the cost of the rake on these bets for these bets to have a positive expected value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can illustrate this with the example of the bets I placed on the 2018 midterms. A significantly more complex and involved strategy could be used to profit from this parlaying opportunity, but this was just a fun example of the concept in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;post-incomplete&#34;&gt;POST INCOMPLETE&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be continued&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winning a Debate: Insights from &#34;Intelligence Squared&#34;</title>
      <link>/post/winning-debate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/winning-debate/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;How does one measure the winner of a debate? If the debate itself is the focus, it’s wholly unsatisfying to just tally up the opinions of the viewers, as that solely reflects the prior beliefs of the audience. “Intelligence Squared” is an excellent podcast which teaches policy through moderated debate. A resolution is proposed (e.g. “Affirmative Action does more harm than good”), and two teams of two experts argue the issue in a structured setting. Many other programs aim for balance with a halfhearted attempt to pay lip service to the opposing side (without truly believing it), so it’s refreshing to hear passionate and informed argument from both sides of the aisle. If one side cites a misleading statistic, their opponents are ready to actually call them out on it, penalizing the lazy rhetorical tactics that plague discourse in an echo chamber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus of the program is the debate itself, but some nominal winner must still be declared. This is determined using a simple formula. The audience is polled before and after the debate (For, Against, or Undecided on the issue), and the side which gains the most votes is the winner. To be clear, I do not think that this method of declaring a winner is a particularly important to the show, nor do I think any listeners actually consider the swings of audience opinion to be the final say on the matter. But it’s still interesting to consider whether or not this is a reasonable way to declare a debate winner. And more broadly, what can the results of a debate tell us about the way that people make up their minds on polarizing issues? Much has been written about the politically charged climate of the present, and the ways in which the media we consume is entrenching us in our positions, leading to static and polarized political views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Intelligence Squared doesn’t just measure the change in support for each side before and after the debate, for events since 2012 it also measured the individual shifts between each category (i.e. “Undecided before and For after”, or “For before and Against after”). This provides a small but insightful dataset looking at the ways in which minds can change on a polarizing issue in the course of an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-does-it-mean-to-win-a-debate&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What does it mean to “win” a debate?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intelligence Squared declares their nominal winner with a simple metric, measuring whether the For or Against side had the largest absolute percentage point shift in support from the pre debate to the post debate audience poll. Thus, if the For side originally had 40% support and the Against side 35% support before the debate, and after the debate the For side had 45% support and the Against side had 43% support, the 8 percentage point increase of the Against side trumps the 5 percentage point increase of the For side, and the Against side wins the night. We will refer to this method for determining a victory as the ISM (Intelligence Squared Metric).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this approach stems from the fact that &lt;em&gt;there are a variety of ways that opinions could shift between the three camps&lt;/em&gt;. This is related to both its usage of absolute percentage point change (with no reference to the relative switch), as well as the presence of the undecided voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://stats.stackexchange.com/a/94742&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; excellent post by &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt; on StackExchange. I have the pleasure of knowing &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt; in person, and in characteristic fashion he gives a thorough and insightful analysis of the ways in which we can have different shifts in support (among the different groups) for the same absolute result, in ways that make determining the winner quite difficult. We cite a simple example proposed by &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt; in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider a situation where originally 20% are For, 60% are Against, and 20% are undecided (we will write this as a vector &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\((.2, .6, .2)\)&lt;/span&gt;). After the debate, the vector of support is &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\((.3, .4, .3)\)&lt;/span&gt;. Under the ISM, this is a clear and decisive win for the For side, as they gained 10 percentage points of support, while the Against side lost 20 percentage points. However, there are a variety of between-group opinion switches that could lead to this result. &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt; suggests that we write these between-group switches in a 3x3 transition matrix, where the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(ij\)&lt;/span&gt;th element represents the percent of the original supporters for the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(i\)&lt;/span&gt;th camp before the debate are supporters of the &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(j\)&lt;/span&gt;th camp after the debate (with For as 1, Against as 2, and Undecided as 3). Then, this represents a plausible transition matrix for our final result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\mathbb{A} = \left(
\begin{array}{ccc}
 0.32 &amp;amp; 0.29 &amp;amp; 0.32 \\
 0.36 &amp;amp; 0.42 &amp;amp; 0.36 \\
 0.32 &amp;amp; 0.29 &amp;amp; 0.32 \\
\end{array}
\right).
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt; explains,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, 36% of the “Fors” changed to the other side while only 29% of the “Against” changed to the opposite opinion. Moreover, slightly more of the undecideds (36%) vs 32%) came out “against” rather than for. Although their numbers in this audience decreased, we have a situation (reminiscent of Simpson’s Paradox) in which the “Against” faction clearly won the debate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a possible outcome where Intelligence Squared would declare the “For” side a decisive winner, but in terms of percentage shifts, the “Against” side was more persuasive at both convincing Undecideds to join their side, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; convincing those with a prior opinion to change their viewpoint. This clarifies the challenge inherent in determining the winner of a debate. When one side is initially quite unpopular, they have a larger population of possible voters that they can woo, which makes their proportional gains much higher in absolute terms. There’s certainly a plausible argument that absolute shifts in support should be the most important factor in determining a winner, but this does make the situation more complex. And it gets even messier in cases where the sub-group switches don’t necessarily agree. We might see one side sway a much larger proportion of the Undecided voters, while being less successful at convincing those from the other side to switch. This could leave us without a conclusive winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-has-this-worked-in-practice&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How has this worked in practice?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the results of the Intelligence Squared debates in reality, we see that the majority of results are uncontroversial. and there is little doubt which side was more convincing. In total, we gather the results from 88 debates from the Intelligence Squared &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;, with the process described &lt;a href=&#34;https://dylanpotteroconnell.github.io/debateresults2/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the unpolished scraped dataset &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dylanpotteroconnell/IntelSquaredProject/blob/master/votingresultsfinal.csv&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first winning metric we consider is the Intelligence Squared Metric (ISM), which measures shift in absolute percentage of support. We next consider the Undisputed Metric (UDM), which uses the proportional switching outlined above, and only assigns a winner when one side &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; convinces a greater proportion of Undecided voters to join their side, as well as a greater proportion of the other side to switch their opinion. In cases when these do not agree, no winner is declared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus the first question is whether there are cases where the UDM declares a winner which is the reverse of the ISM, like the toy example outlined above by &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt;. It turns out that this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an idle concern, and in fact there have been six debates with this conflicting result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- \begin{table}[h] --&gt;
&lt;!--     \centering --&gt;
&lt;!--     \begin{tabular}{|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|l|} --&gt;
&lt;!--     \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         Title &amp; Date &amp; Pre \%: For &amp; Pre \%: Against &amp; Pre \%: Undecided &amp; Abs. \% \$$\backslash$Delta\$: For &amp; Abs. \% \$$\backslash$Delta\$: Against &amp; ISM Winner &amp; UDM Winner \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         Trigger Warning: Safe Spaces Are Dangerous &amp; 06/23/2018 &amp; 57 &amp; 25 &amp; 18 &amp; -1 &amp; 10 &amp; Against &amp; For \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         Preserve Net Neutrality: All Data is Created Equal &amp; 04/17/2018 &amp; 60 &amp; 23 &amp; 17 &amp; 0 &amp; 8 &amp; Against &amp; For \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         Legalize Assisted Suicide &amp; 11/03/2014 &amp; 63 &amp; 11 &amp; 26 &amp; 4 &amp; 11 &amp; Against &amp; For \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         Break up the Big Banks &amp; 10/16/2013 &amp; 35 &amp; 19 &amp; 46 &amp; 13 &amp; 20 &amp; Against &amp; For \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         Cutting the Pentagon&#39;s Budget is a Gift to our Enemies &amp; 06/19/2013 &amp; 20 &amp; 58 &amp; 22 &amp; 9 &amp; 8 &amp; For &amp; Against \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--         The GOP must Seize the Center or Die &amp; 04/17/2013 &amp; 63 &amp; 14 &amp; 23 &amp; 2 &amp; 14 &amp; Against &amp; For \\ \hline --&gt;
&lt;!--     \end{tabular} --&gt;
&lt;!-- \end{table} --&gt;
&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;border-color:#ccc;}
.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#fff;}
.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:#ccc;color:#333;background-color:#f0f0f0;}
.tg .tg-yp4a{border-color:#333333;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-us36{border-color:inherit;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-fraq{color:#333333;border-color:#000000;vertical-align:top}
.tg .tg-dvpl{border-color:inherit;text-align:right;vertical-align:top}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;tg&#34;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Title
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Date
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
Pre %: For
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
Pre %: Against
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
Pre %: Undecided
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
Abs. % &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\Delta\)&lt;/span&gt;: For
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
Abs. % &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\Delta\)&lt;/span&gt;: Against
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
ISM Winner
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
UDM Winner
&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Trigger Warning: Safe Spaces Are Dangerous
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
06/23/2018
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
57
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
25
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
18
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
-1
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
10
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Against
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
For
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Preserve Net Neutrality: All Data is Created Equal
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
04/17/2018
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
60
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
17
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Against
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
For
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Legalize Assisted Suicide
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
11/03/2014
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
63
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
26
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
4
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
11
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Against
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
For
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Break up the Big Banks
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
10/16/2013
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
35
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
19
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
46
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
13
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
20
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Against
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
For
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Cutting the Pentagon’s Budget is a Gift to our Enemies
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
06/19/2013
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
20
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
58
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
22
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
9
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
For
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Against
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
The GOP must Seize the Center or Die
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
04/17/2013
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
63
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-fraq&#34;&gt;
14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-yp4a&#34;&gt;
23
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
2
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-dvpl&#34;&gt;
14
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
Against
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;tg-us36&#34;&gt;
For
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not surprising when the absolute percentage changes are so close (such as in “Cutting the Pentagon’s budget…”), but the other debates show some wildly divergent results. We even see an example of &lt;em&gt;whuber&lt;/em&gt;’s hypothesized situation. In the “Trigger Warnings” debate on 06/23/2018, we see the For camp lose support, the Against camp gain support, and yet we see that the For camp was declared the winner by the UDM. The transition matrix for this debate is shown here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[
\text{Trigger Warnings Debate: }\left(
\begin{array}{ccc}
0.67 &amp;amp; 0.44 &amp;amp; 0.39 \\ 
0.26 &amp;amp; 0.56 &amp;amp; 0.33 \\ 
0.07 &amp;amp; 0.00 &amp;amp; 0.28 \\ 
\end{array}
\right).
\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The For camp was able to lure 39% of the Undecided voters, compared to only 33% by the Against camp. And the For side was able to convince 44% of the Against camp to change their minds, while the Against camp convinced only 26% of the For camp to swap. And yet the For camp &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; support, while the Against camp gained support. This can easily be explained by the initial disparity in popularity. The For side began with 57% of the vote, so while they convinced a larger proportion of Undecided and Against voters to change their view, they had a minority of the audience who were even available to sway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a perfect example of the issue, because it feels fundamentally wrong to declare the winner of the debate to be a side that &lt;em&gt;lost&lt;/em&gt; popularity during the course of the night. This cousin of Simpson’s Paradox defies our intuition, where we want relative and absolute changes to point in the same direction. I think there’s an argument for both sides. The issue with using the UDM (with subgroup proportional shifts) is that there’s an inherent expectation that a debate will shift opinions towards the center. If one group starts overwhelmingly popular, and both sides sway the proportional amount of people to their side, then that side will tend to lose share. It doesn’t make much sense that we would expect any evenly matched debate to bring public opinion towards a 50/50 split, but a series of dead even debates (as measured by the UDM) would push the audience towards that equilibrium point. And yet, we think of the goal of debates as being one of persuasion. And so it makes little sense to declare one side the winner because they had a larger possible audience to persuade, even if their marginal rate of persuasion was inferior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;are-there-obvious-issues-in-the-original-metric&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Are there obvious issues in the original metric?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no singular way to measure the efficacy of these metrics, and it ultimately comes down to our subjective intuition about what it means to “win” a debate. However, we can reasonably agree on some criteria that we intuitively find “fair”. Generally, we want a debate to be a plausibly even playing field from the start. An even more intuitive metric would simply be the popularity of each motion after the debate (which we refer to as the Final Popularity Metric [FPM]), but we reject this approach because it so obviously favors the side that is initially popular with the audience. It’s then worth it to consider whether the ISM is biased in ways that clash with our intuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious plausible bias is that of the initial popularity of each position. In fact, this is why we do not simply use the FPM , so it is perhaps instructive to consider what such bias looks like. We plot the initial popularity of the For and Against positions below, and use color to denote the final winner by the FPM (i.e. which position was ultimately more popular with the audience). Exactly as we’d expect, there is a heavy bias to the initial starting positions. There are a few instances where a particularly large swing allows for the initially unfavorable position to pull out a win, but generally the winner is determined simply by initial popularity, and the processs of the debate itself is largely irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IQ2_FPresults.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![OriginalResults]({{ &#34;/images/IQ2_FPresults.png&#34;}}) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we consider the same plot colored by the standard ISM results, we see a much more promising picture. On first glance, this adjustment does a plausible job of removing the bias from initial popularity. We theorized that the ISM might be punishing to sides that begin with overwhelming popularity, becuase they have so many fewer people that they can convert to their side (and an increase from 90 to 95 percent popularity might only be 5 percentage points, but represents a massive 50% decrease in those who don’t support that side). However, in practice, most positions start at a popularity between 20% and 50%, so those extreme examples just aren’t as concerning. And within that range, the naked eye doesn’t detect any overwhelming patterns of bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IQ2_winnerorigresults.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![OriginalResults]({{ &#34;/images/IQ2_winnerorigresults.png&#34;}}) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One plausible trend that might stand out lies in the bottom right of the chart, where we do note that debates with an initially extremely high For share tended to be won by the Against side. Of the seven debates where the For side began with at least 60% vote share, the Against side won six contests and For won only one. This is a very small sample, but it does fit our intuition, and thus the lack of bias might simply stem from the fact that it is only observed in the extreme starting positions, which occur rarely. We do note that the reverse extreme (where the Against side has initally dominant popularity) does not show any such obvious trend, which makes this slightly less troubling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prior plot only considers the binary outcome under the ISM, but we are not solely concerned with the effect on the binary result, but rather the effect on percentage point change, which can manifest in a shift of binary result. Thus, it must be more illsutrative to break down the effect further. We create 4 bins of debates based on a partition of the initial popularity of the For camp. For each bin, we consider a box plot of the percentage change that the debate creates for the For camp along with the percentage change for the Against camp, which provides a more precise analysis. As before, the picture is muddled until we consider the final bin (debates where the For side enjoyed a 55% or more share of the support), where almost all of the changes to the For side were lesser than the changes for the Against side. This is a much more persuasively troubling result than the simple results observed above, but the sample remains small (only 11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IQ2_partitionvotechange.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![PartitionVoteShare]({{ &#34;/images/IQ2_partitionvotechange.png&#34;}}) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We observe a peculiar result, but are unsure whether it could simply result from random chance. This question of statistical significance is at the heart of the study of statistics. However, it is not immediately clear to me which tool is suited to the situation. A simple comparison of the mean changes of these different bins seems deeply problematic. It is unclear that we can make any plausible assumptions about the distribution of the changes of votes. Crucially, the changes to the For vote share are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; independent to the changes to the Against vote share. And there is a clear confounding variable, where change to For vote share is going to be effected not simply by initial For vote, but by the initial number of undecideds (we certainly have not proven this, but common sense says that an undecided voter is easier to persuade than one who believes in the opposing viewpoint). More broadly, any such test from here is problematic in the way that Exploratory Data Analysis tends to be. We have not rigorously predefined our research question based on a scientific hypothesis, we are simply confirming our vague intuition that starting vote share introduces bias. Thus, a test based on this particular binning creates some form of bias. If we explored deep enough into the data, eventualy we must have found something similarly intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use a nonparametric test to examine the implausibility of the observed trend, but we must keep the bias mentioned above closely in mind. Exploratory data analysis minimizes this problem by relying on standardized statistical tests which answer broad questions. A nonparametric test that examines the statistical implausibility of the difference observed in the arbitrary binning we have chosen above is far less robust. An example statistical test is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilcoxon_signed-rank_test&#34;&gt;Kruskal-Wallis Rank test&lt;/a&gt;. This nonparametric test simply considers the ranked values of the observed data, and considers the statistical probability that we might observe such an extreme disparity as what occurs in our sample. This provides a statistically rigorous result without reliance on assumptions, but the issue is that it provides such an answer to a deeply narrow &lt;em&gt;question&lt;/em&gt;. In our case, we could consider the Kruskal-Wallis test with the changes to the For vote for two groups: those with initial share of 55+%, and those with lesser initial share. In this case, we observe a test statistic of 8.1929, and a p-value of 0.42%. Phrased in statistical language, this means that if our two groups generated changes to the For vote share with the same distribution, there would be less than a one in two hundred chance that we observe at least as large a disaparity in the ranks of the observed values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the question this answers is deceptively narrow. It cannot make any bold claims about &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; debates that begin with 55+% vote share or fewer, but only the ones which we observe. If we had an ideal sample of such debates, and considered those above and below this threshold, then such a statement would be extremely powerful. Instead, our initial sample size of 11 debates means it is quite plausible that there are other fundamental differences in these samples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the Kruskal-Wallis test demonstrates the statistical significance in the difference of the distribution of these samples, but makes no claim as to why. And we have little conclusive proof that it is the prior vote share of the For side that creates this disparity, it could be any number of differences between the populations that provides the root cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
We can stick to a nonparametric test to sidestep of our lack of reasonable assumptions, but we must keep the above concerns closely in mind during this work. This will provide a useful benchmark for the improbability of the observed result, but there will be subjective choices made in the construction of our test (as there is no singular way to formulate our hypothesis). We must simply make reasonable choices, and keep this issue in mind (an issue at the heart of any statistical test conducted after exploratory data analysis, albeit one that is significantly less concerning when the test being used is cookie cutter and not subjectively defined by the examiner). Such 
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an obviously unsatisfying result, but in the name of intellectual honesty I hesitate to any bolder claim. Qualitatively, I do think that the sum of this analysis makes it very likely that our intuition that those with an initially high For vote share experience notable disadvantage for winning the debate under the metric used by Intelligence Squared. However, these extreme cases come up very rarely, and the ISM seems quite defensible for the purposes of the podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;alternative-metrics&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Alternative Metrics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is of course interesting to consider other metrics that one could use. Outlined above, we consider the Undisputed Metric (UDM), which instead considers the percentage that switch between each camp during the debate. The UDM declares a winner if that side converts both a greater percentage of the other side to swap, as well a greater percentage of the Undecided camp to join theirs. In cases where there is disagreement (e.g. the For side convinces a greater proportion of Against voters to join their side than vice versa, but the Against side convinces a greater proportion of Undecided voters), the UDM simply declares that there is no clear winner. The UDM operates under a fundamentally different mindset: that what matters is not the percentage point change, but the proportion of voters who you sway. As noted above, it is perfectly possible for the UDM to declare the opposite winner to the ISM (this is particularly likely to happen in those cases where one side has initially extreme vote share). We first consider another plot of the debate result under the UDM compared to the initial For and Against vote shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![UDM Box Plot](IQ2_winnerUDMresults.png) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IQ2_winnerUDMresults.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![]({{ &#34;/images/IQ2_winnerUDMresults.png&#34;}}) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the ISM, under the UDM it seems the initial popularities are overly determinative of the final result. But we do observe something of a reverse trend: if an initial side has at least 50% share of the starting vote, now they nearly always win. We again break down this effect by considering the voting shifts for debates binned by their initial For vote share. Now, our object of interest is not simply the percentage point change, but a variety of changes (in this plot, we consider the proportion of initially Against voters who shift to For, Undecided persuaded to join the For camp, and initially For voters who defect to the against side). Note that the coloring is done using our initial For popularity partition, unlike above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IQ2_UDMboxplots.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reflects the effects expected from our initial results. Initially high For popularity tends to imply that they will persuade a higher proportion of Against voters, and that a lower proportion of For voters will defect to Against, while the results for Undecided voters are decidedly muddled. This is what we would expect. A high initial For vote share implies a lower Against vote share, so converting a small number of Against voters shows a lower percentage point change, but a large proportional change. The movement of undecided voters does not follow this pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;summary&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of which side is the winner in a debate is far from straightforward. Our intuition tells us that it should depend on the performance of the debaters, and not simply reflect the initial position of the audience. This is why we do not conduct a simple exit poll on the popularity of each side, which the data shows is massively biased towards the initial popularity of the sides. Unsurprisingly, audience members have extremely strong priors on these hotly contested issues, and an hour of debate does not ovewhelm a lifetime of thought on the matter. Intelligence Squared adjusts for this bias by polling the audience before the debate, and considering the percentage point change that each side observe. We hypothesize that this may instead be biased to disfavor initially popular sides. This appears to occur in the observed data, but extreme initial popularity is relatively rare, so it is hard to precisely prove the magnitude of this effect. In fact, the data shows that this metric seems to be a reasonably fair benchmark in practice. We outline one alternative for determining the winner, which is to consider the proportional changes among each sides. Counterintuitively, it is perfectly possible for one side in a debate to lose under the Intelligence Squared system, and yet persuade a greater proportion of both Undecideds and the other side to defect. In fact, we observe this scenario in a number of debates that occur. In practice, following this metric appears to bias results in the opposite manner, where initially popular sides are again favored (although in a similarly plausibly fair way in all but extreme cases). It is worth keeping in mind that the metric used by Intelligence Squared is but one reasonable choice, and while it serves their purposes well, it should not be considered the ultimate determination of efficacy in debate. Luckily, no one would doubt that the experience of the debate is what matters, and the mark of a winner is simply a superficial afterthought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping the &#34;Intelligence Squared&#34; Debate Results</title>
      <link>/post/scraping-is2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/scraping-is2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a brief companion to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dylanpotteroconnell.github.io/debatefinalsummary/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; analyzing the methods of assigning a winner to a debate, using the Intelligence Squared dataset. I will briefly outline here how I assemble that dataset, for trasparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;compiling-the-pages&#34;&gt;Compiling the Pages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results from each Intelligence Squared debate are posted online in pages such as 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.intelligencesquaredus.org/debates/globalization-has-undermined-americas-working-class&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, including video of the debate, a description of the major positions of each side, the qualifications of the debaters, and most importantly, the results of the audience polling. Unfortunately, there doesn’t seem to be a central hub page that neatly lists all the URLs. However, the desired dataset isn’t huge (about 90 total debates), so there’s no substitute for the occasional work simply manually trawling through the website, and recording the date, name, and URL of each debate in question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;scraping-the-numbers&#34;&gt;Scraping the numbers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have a full list of all the relevant URLs, luckily, the results themselves are generally presented in a consistent format. Thus,  some simple work with regular expressions gathers the data that we need. One such example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;debate_vote_results={&amp;quot;live&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;pre&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:36,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:45,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:19,&amp;quot;w&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;post&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:32,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:61,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:7,&amp;quot;w&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;s&amp;quot;:41,&amp;quot;t&amp;quot;:100,&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:18,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:15,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:3},&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:6,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:38,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:1},&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:8,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:8,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:3}},&amp;quot;online&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;t&amp;quot;:100,&amp;quot;pre&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:50,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:35,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:15,&amp;quot;w&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;post&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:44,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:50,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:6,&amp;quot;w&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:35,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:13,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:2},&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:4,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:27,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:4},&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;f&amp;quot;:6,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;:10,&amp;quot;u&amp;quot;:0}}};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case anyone wants to borrow this sort of simple scrape for their own projects, you can find the code 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dylanpotteroconnell/IntelSquaredProject/blob/master/intelsquareddata.R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, although the approach is extremely messy. Luckily, with R it’s more important to be fast than it is to be clean, and you can use very awkward code as long as you find it readable and clear. Regular expressions like this can grab the relevant numbers that we need, and we store it in one large data frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-R&#34;&gt;gsub(&amp;quot;.*\&amp;quot;f\&amp;quot;:\\{\&amp;quot;f\&amp;quot;:(\\d+\\.*\\d*),\&amp;quot;a\&amp;quot;:(\\d+\\.*\\d*),\&amp;quot;u\&amp;quot;:(\\d+\\.*\\d*).*&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;\\1 \\2 \\3&amp;quot;, post)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we identify the numbers that we’re interested in. With the numbers compiled into one large data frame (which can be viewed in raw form 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dylanpotteroconnell/IntelSquaredProject/blob/master/votingresultsfinal.csv&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for those interested in examining the data themselves). In total, there are 88 debates stretching back to 2012 which have all the information needed. The program itself stretches back further, but they only began tracking the subgroup movements more recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next post, we can actually dive into the data itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OddsConverter Part 3: Uploading to the Chrome Store</title>
      <link>/post/oddsconverter-part3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/oddsconverter-part3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Brief update to the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dylanpotteroconnell.github.io/bettingextension2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;past post&lt;/a&gt;. I knew a few people who wanted to try the extension, so I thought it’d be a fun exercise to go through the process of uploading it to the Chrome store. You can view and add the extension to your own browser 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/odds-converter/klechkhopfnjihobbcfeheooaigjjgdg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This is far from a polished state, given that it was meant to be a quick way to explore something new. However, I do find myself using the finished product a surprising amount, so I thought it was worth keeping on the Webstore. And it’s nice to see how easy Google makes it to upload a simple app.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Odds Converter Part 2: Conversion Webpage</title>
      <link>/post/oddsconverter-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/oddsconverter-part2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;opening-a-new-page&#34;&gt;Opening a New Page&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our simple extension from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dylanpotteroconnell.github.io/bettingextension/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; works quite well to replace text on a page, but whenever text isn&amp;rsquo;t displayed in a nice format (which is true for many mdoern websites), it won&amp;rsquo;t do much good. The hope is to add functionality to it so that the user can easily and manually input the odds that they need. My vision was to let the user right click, and open up a page that lets them impute the odds to convert in a more detailed format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before, I don&amp;rsquo;t know enough about Javascript to start from scratch, so I borrow and adapt from some others online. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/4376167/text-selection-and-display-in-context-menu-chrome-extension&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This StackOverflow answer&lt;/a&gt; provides an example of creating a context menu upon a user right click that is the right structure. Importantly, this also provides a framework for storing any selected text that the user right clicks. The end goal is to let them auto populate our odds converter page, so we leave in that functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;\\ rightClick.js
var selection_callbacks = [];
function getSelection(callback) {
 selection_callbacks.push(callback);
    chrome.tabs.executeScript(null, { file:&amp;quot;selection.js&amp;quot; });
  };
  chrome.extension.onRequest.addListener(function (request) {
    var callback = selection_callbacks.shift();
    callback(request);
  });

function openConverter(selectedText) {
  var serviceCall = &#39;converter.html&#39;
  chrome.tabs.create({ url: serviceCall });
}
var tx = getSelection();
var title = &amp;quot;Convert: &#39;&amp;quot; + tx + &amp;quot;&#39; title&amp;quot;;
var id = chrome.contextMenus.create({
    title: &amp;quot;Convert Odds?&amp;quot;,
    contexts:[&amp;quot;selection&amp;quot;],
    onclick: function(info, tab) {
        openConverter(info.selectionText);
    }
});
console.log(&amp;quot;selection item:&amp;quot; + id);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;\\ selection.js
chrome.extension.sendResponse(convert(window.getSelection().toString()));
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty rote, with small changes from the linked work (and final code 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dylanpotteroconnell/oddsextension/blob/master/replaceScript.js&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Initially, I hoped to perform some calculations with the selected text, and then display the result in the context menu itself. After some trial and error, it seems that this is quite a bit more complicated than it would seem. While you can reference the text in the selection using &amp;ldquo;%s&amp;rdquo;, the issue is that this is passed through our function as the literal string &amp;ldquo;%s&amp;rdquo;, and not the selection itself, until it is displayed (at which point it is replaced by tthe selection). This means we can&amp;rsquo;t easily perform a calculation with it. The underlying challenge is that Chrome wants to display the text on the context menu immediately, so we would need to manually program in a structure that lets it wait for us to convert the text. For now, we instead focusing on simply opening the useful HTML page &amp;ldquo;oddsconverter.html&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;odds-converter-html-page&#34;&gt;Odds Converter HTML Page&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want an HTML page that neatly converts between each sort of odds. For a rough idea of the base template, we borrow 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.daniweb.com/programming/web-development/threads/468068/auto-calculate-two-textfields&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; guide. While their goal is quite unrelated, this form has the neat feature where it calculates its result after &lt;em&gt;each&lt;/em&gt; keystroke. I want this extension to be light and nimble, so I like the idea of it constantly updating based on new input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!doctype html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!-- https://www.daniweb.com/programming/web-development/threads/468068/auto-calculate-two-textfields --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script src=&amp;quot;converter.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;form name=&amp;quot;convert&amp;quot; action=&amp;quot;&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;convert&amp;quot; &amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;span id=&amp;quot;update&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Odds Converter&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot; onkeyup=&amp;quot;convML(this)&amp;quot;/&amp;gt; Money Line &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;frac&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;frac&amp;quot; onkeyup=&amp;quot;convFrac(this)&amp;quot;/&amp;gt; Fractional Odds &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;&amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;ip&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;ip&amp;quot; onkeyup=&amp;quot;convIP(this)&amp;quot;/&amp;gt; Implied Probability &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;hidden&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;total&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;total&amp;quot; value=&amp;quot;0&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/form&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heavy lifting is of course done by the functions stored in the javascript file &amp;ldquo;converter.js&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;function convML(obj) {
  if(/^[\+|-] ?[0-9]+$/.test(obj.value)){
    var pattern = /([+|-]) ?([0-9]+)/;
    var newIP = obj.value.replace(pattern,
      function(fm,$1,$2)
      {
        if ($1==&amp;quot;+&amp;quot;)
        {
          return(Math.round(100.0/(100.0+parseInt($2))*1000)/10.0)
        } else
        {
          return(Math.round(parseInt($2)/(100.0+parseInt($2))*1000)/10.0)
        }
      });
     var newFrac = String(Math.round(100/(newIP/100.0)-100)/100)+&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;+&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;;
     document.getElementById(&#39;ip&#39;).value = newIP;
     document.getElementById(&#39;frac&#39;).value = newFrac;
  }
}

function convFrac(obj) {
  document.getElementById(&#39;ip&#39;).value = obj.value;
// Add decimals

  if(/^[0-9]+\.?[0-9]*\/[0-9]+\.?[0-9]*$/.test(obj.value)){
    var pattern = /([0-9]+\.?[0-9]*)\/([0-9]+\.?[0-9]*)/;
    var newIP  = obj.value.replace(pattern,
                                          function(fm,$1,$2)
                                          {
                                             return(Math.round(1000*parseFloat($2)/(parseFloat($2)+parseFloat($1)))/10.0)
                                          }
                                    );
     document.getElementById(&#39;ip&#39;).value = newIP;
     document.getElementById(&#39;ml&#39;).value = IPtoML(parseFloat(newIP)/100.0);
  }
}
  if(/^[0-9]+\.?[0-9]*$/.test(obj.value)){
    document.getElementById(&#39;ml&#39;).value = IPtoML(parseFloat(obj.value)/100.0);
  }
}

function IPtoML(IP) {
  if (IP &amp;gt; .5) {
    return(&amp;quot;-&amp;quot; + String(Math.round(100.0*IP/(1-IP))))
  } else if (IP &amp;lt;= .5) {
    return(&amp;quot;+&amp;quot;+String(Math.round(100.0/IP - 100)))
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the conversion functions follows the same format: after each keystroke in the text box, check if the given input is of the correct form, and if it is, upate the other two text boxes with the converted odds. The functionality is very limited, but it fulfills our purposes for now. Converting moneyline odds and implied probability to fractional odds is a tougher challenge, so for now we simiply display them as decimals with a denominator of one (while there is no straightforward one to one mapping to fractional odds, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to write an algorithm to make an educated guess as to what whole number odds are closest, but for now we keep it simple).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we open up this HTML page, it works as desired, but when we load it into our extension, it opens up and&amp;hellip; does nothing. None of the fields update themselves, no matter howm much you try. A quick Google search determines that we are barking right up the wrong tree. A few years ago, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/contentSecurityPolicy#JSExecution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chrome banned all inline Javascript&lt;/a&gt; from its extension pages. I have no doubt that they had good security related reasons to do so, but it means that our page as written is quite useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;removing-inline-javascript&#34;&gt;Removing Inline Javascript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that for simple HTML forms like this, the switch is relatively painless. We remove the function calls from the HTML file, so &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot; onkeyup=&amp;quot;convML(this)&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; becomes &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;input type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Then, in our &amp;ldquo;converter.js&amp;rdquo; file, we need to add an EventListener function to process each of these events, based on their ID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;document.addEventListener(&amp;quot;DOMContentLoaded&amp;quot;, function(event) {
  document.getElementById(&amp;quot;ml&amp;quot;).addEventListener(&amp;quot;keyup&amp;quot;, function() {
        convML(document.getElementById(&#39;ml&#39;));
     });
  document.getElementById(&amp;quot;frac&amp;quot;).addEventListener(&amp;quot;keyup&amp;quot;, function() {
        convFrac(document.getElementById(&#39;frac&#39;));
     });
  document.getElementById(&amp;quot;ip&amp;quot;).addEventListener(&amp;quot;keyup&amp;quot;, function() {
        convIP(document.getElementById(&#39;ip&#39;));
     });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of our code can stay the exact same. Once we use the EventListener format, our other Javascript functions work just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OddsConverter Part 1: Converting Plaintext</title>
      <link>/post/oddsconverter-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/oddsconverter-part1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The same betting odds are often displayed in disparate ways, depending on the context. In America, normally in terms of a Moneyline, where +200 is shorthand for &amp;ldquo;if you bet $100, you can win an additional $200&amp;rdquo;. In other contexts, we generally see the tradition &amp;ldquo;X/Y&amp;rdquo; fractional odds. Both of these have clear mathematical meanings, but for inexperienced bettors, they tend to be poor conveyors of intuitive meaning. We can quickly estimate what &amp;ldquo;+350&amp;rdquo; implies, but for most people, it takes a mental calculation to do so. The most useful intuitive information about betting odds comes from the &amp;ldquo;Implied Probability&amp;rdquo;, which is the probability of the event necessary for you to &amp;ldquo;break even&amp;rdquo; on the bet. Betting sites don&amp;rsquo;t particularly like Implied Probability because it makes the cut they take more obvious (when mutually exclusive and complete events have probabilities that sum up to greater than one), and more intuitively accurate information for bettors can make them realize how daunting it is to actually keep up a positive expected value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone without the perfect intuition needed to convert these odds in my head, I got tired of glancing at a table of odds and trying to work out their precise value one by one. I thought it would be nice to have a very simple Google Chrome extension that could do it for me. The initial functionality is simple: click on the icon, and it converts any odds it can find on the page into Implied Probability. Click on it again, and it converts back. The challenge is that I have zero knowledge of JavaScript. Luckily, this task was simple enough that it could be cobbled together in the style of Frankenstein&amp;rsquo;s monster, with some slight modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;click-icon-replace-text&#34;&gt;Click Icon, Replace Text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first feature necessary is simple an extension that runs a script when the icon is clicked. We find a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/7168362/run-script-each-time-chrome-extension-icon-clicked&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stack Overflow question&lt;/a&gt; (which will be the source of the code for most of the extension) with this very task. Every Chrome Extension begins with a manifest.json file, which gives an overview of the permissions and structure of the extension. I grab their initial suggested manifest.json, and make a number of modifications which will become necessary later. The &amp;ldquo;contextmenus&amp;rdquo; under permissions is only necessary to activate context menus within Chrome, which seems like a useful feature but is not yet crucial to the Extension&amp;rsquo;s functionality. I also made a set of three simple icons in GIMP, so that it looks natural in the browser. The key parts here are the two scripts under &amp;ldquo;background&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;rightclick.js&amp;rdquo; provides instructions for how to create a context menu upon right click, which we ignore for now (I played with it, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a work in progress). However, &amp;ldquo;background.js&amp;rdquo; is the script that tells our&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
{
  &amp;quot;manifest_version&amp;quot;: 2,

  &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Convert Odds into Implied Probability&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;description&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Click this icon to convert moneyline odds into implied probability, and vice versa.&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;version&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;background&amp;quot; : {
    &amp;quot;scripts&amp;quot; : [&amp;quot;background.js&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;rightclick.js&amp;quot;]
  },
  &amp;quot;icons&amp;quot;: { &amp;quot;16&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;icon16.png&amp;quot;,
             &amp;quot;48&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;icon48.png&amp;quot;,
             &amp;quot;128&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;icon128.png&amp;quot; },

  &amp;quot;browser_action&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;default_icon&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;icon48.png&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;default_title&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Convert Odds&amp;quot;
  },
  &amp;quot;permissions&amp;quot;: [
    &amp;quot;activeTab&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;contextMenus&amp;quot;
  ]
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key parts here are the two scripts under &amp;ldquo;background&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;rightclick.js&amp;rdquo; provides instructions for how to create a context menu upon right click, which we ignore for now (I played with it, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a work in progress), and &amp;ldquo;background.js&amp;rdquo; is a script that calls our text replace script when the Extension icon is clicked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;chrome.browserAction.onClicked.addListener(function(tab) {
   chrome.tabs.executeScript(null, {file: &amp;quot;replaceScript.js&amp;quot;});
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;replaceScript.js&amp;rdquo; is the script that  runs a text replacement that converts anything that &amp;ldquo;looks like&amp;rdquo; odds into implied probabilities (and you can view the final script 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dylanpotteroconnell/oddsextension/blob/master/replaceScript.js&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Being totally unfamiliar with JavaScript, I grab code from an Extension that performs a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://9to5google.com/2015/06/14/how-to-make-a-chrome-extensions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;simple text replace for each webpage&lt;/a&gt;. The base structure is as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;var elements = document.getElementsByTagName(&#39;*&#39;);
for (var i = 0; i &amp;lt; elements.length; i++) {
    var element = elements[i];
    for (var j = 0; j &amp;lt; element.childNodes.length; j++) {
        var node = element.childNodes[j];
        if (node.nodeType === 3) {
            var pattern = /abc/gi;
            var text = node.nodeValue;
            var replacedText = text.replace(pattern, &#39;def&#39;);
            if (replacedText !== text) {
                element.replaceChild(document.createTextNode(replacedText), node);
            }
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;detect-patterns-calculate-conversions&#34;&gt;Detect Patterns, Calculate Conversions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we can use Regular Expressions to only replace certain structures of characters, rather than just one static string. To start, we want to try and identify sequences of exactly a plus or minus sign, followed by at least one digit (e.g. &amp;ldquo;-220&amp;rdquo;). The parentheses &amp;ldquo;capture&amp;rdquo; the characters inside, as we need to not just find these patterns, but extract the numbers. We want to find the end of the digits, but we want to leave the following character in the page&amp;rsquo;s HTML, so we &amp;ldquo;grab&amp;rdquo; the first nondigit character (the [^0-9), but only if it exists (the &amp;ldquo;?&amp;quot;) using &amp;ldquo;([^0-9]?)&amp;quot;, so that we can place that character after our converted expression, &lt;code&gt;var pattern = /([+|-])([0-9]+)([^0-9]?)/gi;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the challenge is that we want to perform a small calculation using the number provided. That means we need to be able to feed captured characters (preferably, the numbers and the +/- sign) as inputs into a function that determines the output of the replace function of text. I don&amp;rsquo;t know of the optimal way to do this in JavaScript, but with a Google search we find a way to do just that 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bennadel.com/blog/55-using-methods-in-javascript-replace-method.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can replace the previous string used for our pattern with a lambda function. Note that the link provided is inaccurate in its description of the inputs to the lambda function, and this is corrected to the comments. The inputs to the dummy function here are always &amp;ldquo;the full match, $1, $2, $3, &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; (where $X refers to the xth capture element), while in the linked tutorial they use &amp;ldquo;$1$&amp;rdquo; in the function input to refer to the full text. We can adapt their function to convert an American moneyline into its implied odds as follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
var replacedText = text.replace(pattern,
                                function(fm,$1,$2,$3)
				    {
				      if ($1==&amp;quot;+&amp;quot;)
				      {
					return(&amp;quot;|&amp;quot;+String(Math.round(100.0/(100.0+parseInt($2))*1000)/10.0)+&amp;quot;\%&amp;quot;+&amp;quot;|&amp;quot;+$3)
				      } else
				      {
					return(&amp;quot;|&amp;quot;+String(Math.round(parseInt($2)/(100.0+parseInt($2))*1000)/10.0)
						 +&amp;quot;\%&amp;quot;+&amp;quot;|&amp;quot;+$3)
				      }
				    });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s worth breaking this into parts. The inputs to our function are the full text (&amp;lsquo;fm&amp;rsquo;, which we do not use here, but I was not aware of how to suppress this input), and the three strings &amp;lsquo;captured&amp;rsquo; from our regex matching (where $1 refers to the +/- sign, $2 is the number of the line, and $3 is the trailing character). We compute the simple formula to go from a moneyline bet to its implied odds. For a moneyline of +$X, we earn $X+$100 on a win. Thus, the odds (O) needed to break even are $100=0*($X+$100), so O=$100/($X+$100). Similarly, for a moneyline of -$X, we bet $X to win $100, and the implied odds are O=$X/($X+$100). The final return statement is simply cobbled together from some JavaScript documentation. ParseInt turns the &amp;lsquo;$2&amp;rsquo; input into an integer, we then multiply by 1000, and divide by 10 to get the result in the form of a percentage with a single decimal place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We repeat this process with two other conversions: 2. Fractional Odds (i.e. &amp;ldquo;3/1&amp;rdquo;) to Implied Probability, and 3. &amp;ldquo;Undoing&amp;rdquo; our first conversion, converting implied probabilities back into moneyline odds. We do not include a separate &amp;ldquo;undo&amp;rdquo; conversion for Fractional Odds, because I wanted to keep this extension very minimal, and detecting the most accurate Fractional Odds to a rounded decimal percentage is a less straightforward conversion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;next&#34;&gt;Next&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This results in a simple but effective Chrome Extension that can save quite a bit of time. When on a page with odds in HTML text, you tap the button and can quickly see them replaced by their Implied Probabilities. The major downside is that more complex websites don&amp;rsquo;t always show their odds in such simple HTML text, and learning to detect them for the major bookmakers would be a more substantial challenge. However, most people encounter odds referenced in articles or text discussions, where this Extension works quite cleanly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an R Markdown document. Markdown is a simple formatting syntax for authoring HTML, PDF, and MS Word documents. For more details on using R Markdown see &lt;a href=&#34;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can embed an R code chunk like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(cars)
##      speed           dist       
##  Min.   : 4.0   Min.   :  2.00  
##  1st Qu.:12.0   1st Qu.: 26.00  
##  Median :15.0   Median : 36.00  
##  Mean   :15.4   Mean   : 42.98  
##  3rd Qu.:19.0   3rd Qu.: 56.00  
##  Max.   :25.0   Max.   :120.00
fit &amp;lt;- lm(dist ~ speed, data = cars)
fit
## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = dist ~ speed, data = cars)
## 
## Coefficients:
## (Intercept)        speed  
##     -17.579        3.932&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;including-plots&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Including Plots&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also embed plots. See Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:pie&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;par(mar = c(0, 1, 0, 1))
pie(
  c(280, 60, 20),
  c(&amp;#39;Sky&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Sunny side of pyramid&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Shady side of pyramid&amp;#39;),
  col = c(&amp;#39;#0292D8&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#F7EA39&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;#C4B632&amp;#39;),
  init.angle = -50, border = NA
)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:pie&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2015-07-23-r-rmarkdown_files/figure-html/pie-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;A fancy pie chart.&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: A fancy pie chart.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TEST Writing technical content in Academic</title>
      <link>/post/writing-technical-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/writing-technical-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Academic is designed to give technical content creators a seamless experience. You can focus on the content and Academic handles the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlight your code snippets, take notes on math classes, and draw diagrams from textual representation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this page, you&amp;rsquo;ll find some examples of the types of technical content that can be rendered with Academic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;code&#34;&gt;Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic supports a Markdown extension for highlighting code syntax. You can enable this feature by toggling the &lt;code&gt;highlight&lt;/code&gt; option in your &lt;code&gt;config/_default/params.toml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```python
import pandas as pd
data = pd.read_csv(&amp;quot;data.csv&amp;quot;)
data.head()
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import pandas as pd
data = pd.read_csv(&amp;quot;data.csv&amp;quot;)
data.head()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic supports a Markdown extension for $\LaTeX$ math. You can enable this feature by toggling the &lt;code&gt;math&lt;/code&gt; option in your &lt;code&gt;config/_default/params.toml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To render &lt;em&gt;inline&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;block&lt;/em&gt; math, wrap your LaTeX math with &lt;code&gt;$...$&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;$$...$$&lt;/code&gt;, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example &lt;strong&gt;math block&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-tex&#34;&gt;$$\gamma_{n} = \frac{ 
\left | \left (\mathbf x_{n} - \mathbf x_{n-1} \right )^T 
\left [\nabla F (\mathbf x_{n}) - \nabla F (\mathbf x_{n-1}) \right ] \right |}
{\left \|\nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n}) - \nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n-1}) \right \|^2}$$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\gamma_{n} = \frac{ \left | \left (\mathbf x_{n} - \mathbf x_{n-1} \right )^T \left [\nabla F (\mathbf x_{n}) - \nabla F (\mathbf x_{n-1}) \right ] \right |}{\left |\nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n}) - \nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n-1}) \right |^2}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example &lt;strong&gt;inline math&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;$\nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n})$&lt;/code&gt; renders as $\nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n})$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example &lt;strong&gt;multi-line math&lt;/strong&gt; using the &lt;code&gt;\\\\&lt;/code&gt; math linebreak:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-tex&#34;&gt;$$f(k;p_0^*) = \begin{cases} p_0^* &amp;amp; \text{if }k=1, \\\\
1-p_0^* &amp;amp; \text {if }k=0.\end{cases}$$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$f(k;p_0^*) = \begin{cases} p_0^* &amp;amp; \text{if }k=1, \\&lt;br&gt;
1-p_0^* &amp;amp; \text {if }k=0.\end{cases}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;diagrams&#34;&gt;Diagrams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic supports a Markdown extension for diagrams. You can enable this feature by toggling the &lt;code&gt;diagram&lt;/code&gt; option in your &lt;code&gt;config/_default/params.toml&lt;/code&gt; file or by adding &lt;code&gt;diagram: true&lt;/code&gt; to your page front matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example &lt;strong&gt;flowchart&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```mermaid
graph TD
A[Hard] --&amp;gt;|Text| B(Round)
B --&amp;gt; C{Decision}
C --&amp;gt;|One| D[Result 1]
C --&amp;gt;|Two| E[Result 2]
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-mermaid&#34;&gt;graph TD
A[Hard] --&amp;gt;|Text| B(Round)
B --&amp;gt; C{Decision}
C --&amp;gt;|One| D[Result 1]
C --&amp;gt;|Two| E[Result 2]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example &lt;strong&gt;sequence diagram&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```mermaid
sequenceDiagram
Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;John: Hello John, how are you?
loop Healthcheck
    John-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;John: Fight against hypochondria
end
Note right of John: Rational thoughts!
John--&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Alice: Great!
John-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: How about you?
Bob--&amp;gt;&amp;gt;John: Jolly good!
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-mermaid&#34;&gt;sequenceDiagram
Alice-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;John: Hello John, how are you?
loop Healthcheck
    John-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;John: Fight against hypochondria
end
Note right of John: Rational thoughts!
John--&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Alice: Great!
John-&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Bob: How about you?
Bob--&amp;gt;&amp;gt;John: Jolly good!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example &lt;strong&gt;Gantt diagram&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```mermaid
gantt
section Section
Completed :done,    des1, 2014-01-06,2014-01-08
Active        :active,  des2, 2014-01-07, 3d
Parallel 1   :         des3, after des1, 1d
Parallel 2   :         des4, after des1, 1d
Parallel 3   :         des5, after des3, 1d
Parallel 4   :         des6, after des4, 1d
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-mermaid&#34;&gt;gantt
section Section
Completed :done,    des1, 2014-01-06,2014-01-08
Active        :active,  des2, 2014-01-07, 3d
Parallel 1   :         des3, after des1, 1d
Parallel 2   :         des4, after des1, 1d
Parallel 3   :         des5, after des3, 1d
Parallel 4   :         des6, after des4, 1d
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example &lt;strong&gt;class diagram&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```mermaid
classDiagram
Class01 &amp;lt;|-- AveryLongClass : Cool
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;interface&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Class01
Class09 --&amp;gt; C2 : Where am i?
Class09 --* C3
Class09 --|&amp;gt; Class07
Class07 : equals()
Class07 : Object[] elementData
Class01 : size()
Class01 : int chimp
Class01 : int gorilla
class Class10 {
  &amp;lt;&amp;lt;service&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
  int id
  size()
}
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-mermaid&#34;&gt;classDiagram
Class01 &amp;lt;|-- AveryLongClass : Cool
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;interface&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Class01
Class09 --&amp;gt; C2 : Where am i?
Class09 --* C3
Class09 --|&amp;gt; Class07
Class07 : equals()
Class07 : Object[] elementData
Class01 : size()
Class01 : int chimp
Class01 : int gorilla
class Class10 {
  &amp;lt;&amp;lt;service&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
  int id
  size()
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example &lt;strong&gt;state diagram&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```mermaid
stateDiagram
[*] --&amp;gt; Still
Still --&amp;gt; [*]
Still --&amp;gt; Moving
Moving --&amp;gt; Still
Moving --&amp;gt; Crash
Crash --&amp;gt; [*]
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-mermaid&#34;&gt;stateDiagram
[*] --&amp;gt; Still
Still --&amp;gt; [*]
Still --&amp;gt; Moving
Moving --&amp;gt; Still
Moving --&amp;gt; Crash
Crash --&amp;gt; [*]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;todo-lists&#34;&gt;Todo lists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can even write your todo lists in Academic too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;- [x] Write math example
- [x] Write diagram example
- [ ] Do something else
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Write math example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Write diagram example&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Do something else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tables&#34;&gt;Tables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Represent your data in tables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;| First Header  | Second Header |
| ------------- | ------------- |
| Content Cell  | Content Cell  |
| Content Cell  | Content Cell  |
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;First Header&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Second Header&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Content Cell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Content Cell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Content Cell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Content Cell&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;asides&#34;&gt;Asides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic supports a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/#alerts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shortcode for asides&lt;/a&gt;, also referred to as &lt;em&gt;notices&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;hints&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;alerts&lt;/em&gt;. By wrapping a paragraph in &lt;code&gt;{{% alert note %}} ... {{% /alert %}}&lt;/code&gt;, it will render as an aside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% alert note %}}
A Markdown aside is useful for displaying notices, hints, or definitions to your readers.
{{% /alert %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    A Markdown aside is useful for displaying notices, hints, or definitions to your readers.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;icons&#34;&gt;Icons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic enables you to use a wide range of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/page-builder/#icons&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;icons from &lt;em&gt;Font Awesome&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Academicons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in addition to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/#emojis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;emojis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples using the &lt;code&gt;icon&lt;/code&gt; shortcode to render icons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; icon name=&amp;quot;terminal&amp;quot; pack=&amp;quot;fas&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}} Terminal  
{{&amp;lt; icon name=&amp;quot;python&amp;quot; pack=&amp;quot;fab&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}} Python  
{{&amp;lt; icon name=&amp;quot;r-project&amp;quot; pack=&amp;quot;fab&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}} R
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;renders as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-terminal  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Terminal&lt;br&gt;

  &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-python  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Python&lt;br&gt;

  &lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-r-project  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; R&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;did-you-find-this-page-helpful-consider-sharing-it-&#34;&gt;Did you find this page helpful? Consider sharing it 🙌&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic: the website builder for Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a free website with Academic using Markdown, Jupyter, or RStudio. Choose a beautiful color theme and build anything with the Page Builder - over 40 &lt;em&gt;widgets&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;themes&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;language packs&lt;/em&gt; included!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic-demo.netlify.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Check out the latest &lt;strong&gt;demo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of what you&amp;rsquo;ll get in less than 10 minutes, or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/#expo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;view the &lt;strong&gt;showcase&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of personal, project, and business sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👉 
&lt;a href=&#34;#install&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get Started&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;📚 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;View the &lt;strong&gt;documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;💬 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://discourse.gohugo.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask a question&lt;/strong&gt; on the forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👥 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://spectrum.chat/academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chat with the &lt;strong&gt;community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🐦 Twitter: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/source_themes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@source_themes&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/GeorgeCushen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@GeorgeCushen&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23MadeWithAcademic&amp;amp;src=typd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;#MadeWithAcademic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;💡 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic/issues&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Request a &lt;strong&gt;feature&lt;/strong&gt; or report a &lt;strong&gt;bug&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;⬆️ &lt;strong&gt;Updating?&lt;/strong&gt; View the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Update Guide&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/updates/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Release Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;❤️ &lt;strong&gt;Support development&lt;/strong&gt; of Academic:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;☕️ 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://paypal.me/cushen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donate a coffee&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;💵 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.patreon.com/cushen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Become a backer on &lt;strong&gt;Patreon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🖼️ 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redbubble.com/people/neutreno/works/34387919-academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Decorate your laptop or journal with an Academic &lt;strong&gt;sticker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👕 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.threadless.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wear the &lt;strong&gt;T-shirt&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👩‍💻 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/contribute/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contribute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-academic-is-mobile-first-with-a-responsive-design-to-ensure-that-your-site-looks-stunning-on-every-device&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gcushen/hugo-academic/master/academic.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Academic is mobile first with a responsive design to ensure that your site looks stunning on every device.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/gcushen/hugo-academic/master/academic.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Academic is mobile first with a responsive design to ensure that your site looks stunning on every device.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key features:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Page builder&lt;/strong&gt; - Create &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/page-builder/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;widgets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;elements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit any type of content&lt;/strong&gt; - Blog posts, publications, talks, slides, projects, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create content&lt;/strong&gt; in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/jupyter/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jupyter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/install/#install-with-rstudio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RStudio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plugin System&lt;/strong&gt; - Fully customizable 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/themes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;color&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;font themes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Display Code and Math&lt;/strong&gt; - Code highlighting and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/LaTeX/Mathematics&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LaTeX math&lt;/a&gt; supported&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrations&lt;/strong&gt; - 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://analytics.google.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Disqus commenting&lt;/a&gt;, Maps, Contact Forms, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beautiful Site&lt;/strong&gt; - Simple and refreshing one page design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry-Leading SEO&lt;/strong&gt; - Help get your website found on search engines and social media&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media Galleries&lt;/strong&gt; - Display your images and videos with captions in a customizable gallery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile Friendly&lt;/strong&gt; - Look amazing on every screen with a mobile friendly version of your site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-language&lt;/strong&gt; - 15+ language packs including English, 中文, and Português&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-user&lt;/strong&gt; - Each author gets their own profile page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy Pack&lt;/strong&gt; - Assists with GDPR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stand Out&lt;/strong&gt; - Bring your site to life with animation, parallax backgrounds, and scroll effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One-Click Deployment&lt;/strong&gt; - No servers. No databases. Only files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic comes with &lt;strong&gt;automatic day (light) and night (dark) mode&lt;/strong&gt; built-in. Alternatively, visitors can  choose their preferred mode - click the sun/moon icon in the top right of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic-demo.netlify.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Demo&lt;/a&gt; to see it in action! Day/night mode can also be disabled by the site admin in &lt;code&gt;params.toml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/themes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Choose a stunning &lt;strong&gt;theme&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;font&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for your site. Themes are fully 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/customization/#custom-theme&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;customizable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecosystem&#34;&gt;Ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sourcethemes/academic-admin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academic Admin&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; An admin tool to import publications from BibTeX or import assets for an offline site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sourcethemes/academic-scripts&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academic Scripts&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Scripts to help migrate content to new versions of Academic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;install&#34;&gt;Install&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can choose from one of the following four methods to install:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/install/#install-with-web-browser&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;one-click install using your web browser (recommended)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/install/#install-with-git&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;install on your computer using &lt;strong&gt;Git&lt;/strong&gt; with the Command Prompt/Terminal app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/install/#install-with-zip&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;install on your computer by downloading the &lt;strong&gt;ZIP files&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/install/#install-with-rstudio&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;install on your computer with &lt;strong&gt;RStudio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/get-started/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;personalize and deploy your new site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;updating&#34;&gt;Updating&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/update/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;View the Update Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to &lt;em&gt;star&lt;/em&gt; the project on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; to help keep track of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/updates&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;updates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;license&#34;&gt;License&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copyright 2016-present 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://georgecushen.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;George Cushen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Released under the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gcushen/hugo-academic/blob/master/LICENSE.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;MIT&lt;/a&gt; license.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
